<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about compiler)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/compiler.xml" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 13:41:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Disappointing zapcc performance on Deep Learning Library (DLL)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/03/disappointing-zapcc-performance-on-deep-learning-library-dll.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;One week ago, zapcc 1.0 was released and I've observed it to be much faster than the other
compilers in terms of compile time. This can be seen when
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/03/release-zapcc-10-fast-cpp-compiler.html"&gt;I tested it on my Expression Templates Library (ETL)&lt;/a&gt;. It was almost four
times faster than clang 3.9 and about 2.5 times faster than GCC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ETL library is quite heavy to compile, but still reasonable. This is not the
case for my Deep Learning Library (DLL) where compiling all the test cases takes
a very long time. I have to admit that I have been going overboard with
templates and such and I have now to pay the price. In practice, for the users
of the library, this is not a big problem since only one or two neural networks
will be compiled (and it will take hours to train), but in the test cases, there
are hundreds of them and this is a huge pain. Anyway, enough with the ramble,
I figured it would be very good to test zapcc on it and see what I can gain from
using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, when I speak of a compiler thread, I mean an instance of the
processor, so it's really a process in the Linux world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="results"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I soon realized that I would have more issues than I thought. The first
problem is the memory consumed by zapcc. Indeed, it is based on clang and
I always had problem with huge memory consumption from clang on this library and
zapcc has even bigger memory consumption because some information is cached
between runs. The amount of memory that zapcc is able to cache can be configured
in the configuration file. By default, it can use 1.5Go of memory. When zapcc
goes over the memory limit, it simply wipes out its caches. This means that all
the gain for the next compilation will be lost, since the cache will have to be
rebuilt from scratch. This is not a hard limit for the compilation itself.
Indeed, if the compilation itself takes 3Go, it will still be able to complete
it, but it is likely that the cache will be wiped after the compilation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tried compiling using several threads, it soon used all my memory and
crashed. The same occurs with clang but I can still compile with 3 or 4 threads
without too much issues on this computer. The same also occurs with GCC but it
can still handle 4 or 5 threads (depending on the order of the compilation
units).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tests are performed on my desktop computer at work, which is not really
good... I have 12Go of RAM (I had to ask for extra...) and an old Sandy Bridge
processor, but at least I have an SSD (also had to ask for extra).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with testing with only one compiler thread. For zapcc, I set the
maximum memory limit to 8Go. Even with such a limit, the zapcc server restarted
more than 10 times during the compilation of the 84 test cases. After this first
experiment, I increased the number of threads to 2 for each compiler, using 4Go
limit for zapcc. The limit is for each server and each parallel thread will
spawn a new server, so the effective limit is the number of threads times the
limit. Even with two threads, I was unable to finish a compilation with zapcc.
This is quite disappoint for me since clang is able to run with 4 threads in
parallel. Moreover, a big problem with that is that the servers are not always
killed when there is no no more memory, they just hang and use all the memory of
the computer, which is evidently really inconvenient for service processes. When
this happens with clang or gcc, the compiler simply crashes and the memory is
released and make is interrupted. Since zapcc is not able to work with more than
one thread on this computer, the results are the ones with one thread. I was
also surprised to be able to compile the library with clang and four threads,
this was not possible before clang-3.9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="36%"&gt;
&lt;col width="17%"&gt;
&lt;col width="17%"&gt;
&lt;col width="15%"&gt;
&lt;col width="15%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;gcc-4.9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2250.95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1256.36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;912.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;760.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;gcc-5.3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2305.37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1279.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;918.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;741.38&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang-3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2047.61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1102.93&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;899.13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;730.42&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc-1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1483.73&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1483.73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1483.73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1483.73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Difference against Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-27.55%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+25.69%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+39.37%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+50.77%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC-5.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-35.66%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+13.75%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+38.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+50.03%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC-4.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-34.08%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+15.30%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+38.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+48.75%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at the results with only one thread, we can see that there still are
some significant improvements when using zapcc, but nowhere near as good as what
was seen in the compilation of ETL. Here, the compilation time is reduced by 34%
compared to gcc and by 27% compared to clang. This is not bad, since it is
faster than the other compilers, but I would have expected better speedups. We
can see that g++-4.9 is slightly faster than g++-5.3, but this is not really
a significant difference. I'm actually very surprised to find that clang is
faster than g++ on this experiment. On ETL, it is always very significantly
slower and before, it was also significantly slower on DLL. I was so used to
this, that I stopped using it on this project. I may have to reconsider my
position when working on this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the results with more than two threads. Even with two threads,
every compiler is faster than zapcc. Indeed, zapcc is slower than Clang by 25%
and slower than GCC by about 15%. If we use more threads, the other compilers
are becoming even faster and the slowdowns of zapcc are more important. When
using four threads, zapcc is about 48% slower than gcc and about 50% slower than
clang. This is really showing one big downside of zapcc that has a very large
memory consumption. When it is used to compile really heavy template code, it is
failing very early to use more processes. And even when there is enough memory,
the speedups are not as great as for relatively simpler code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One may argue that this is not a fair comparison since zapcc does not have the
same numbers of threads. However, considering that this is the best zapcc can do
on this machine, I would argue that this is a fair comparison in this limited
experimental setting. If we were to have a big machine for compilation, which
I don't have at work, the zapcc results would likely be more interesting, but in
this specific limited case, it shows that zapcc suffers from its high memory
consumption. It should also be taken into account that this experiment was done
with almost nothing else running on the machine (no browser for instance) to
have as much memory as possible available for the compilers. This is not
a common use case.  Most of the days, when I compile something, I have my
browser open, which makes a large difference in memory available, and several
other applications (but consoles and vim instances do not really consume memory
:D).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experiment made me realize that the compilation times for this library were
quickly becoming crazy. Most of the time, the complete test suite is only
compiled on my Continuous Integration machine at home which has a much faster
processor and much more RAM. Therefore, it is relatively fast since it uses more
threads to compile.  Nevertheless, this is not a good point that the unit tests
takes so much time to compile. I plan to split the test cases in several sets.
Because, currently the real unit tests are compiled with the performance tests
and other various tests. I'll probably end up generating three executables. This
will help greatly during development. Moreover, I also have a technique to
decrease the compilation time by erasing some template parameters at compilation
time. This is already ready, but has currently a runtime overhead that I will
try to remove and then use this technique everywhere to get back to reasonable
compilation times. I'll also try to see if I can find obvious compilation
bottlenecks in the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, while zapcc brings some very interesting compilation speedups in
some cases like in my ETL library, it also has some downsides, namely
&lt;strong&gt;huge memory consumption&lt;/strong&gt;. This memory consumption may prevent the use of several
compiler threads and render zapcc much less interesting than other compilers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When trying to compile my DLL library on a machine with 12Go of RAM with two
zapcc threads, it was impossible for me to make it complete. While zapcc was
faster with one thread than the other compilers, they were able to use up to
four threads and in the end &lt;strong&gt;zapcc was about twice slower than clang&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew that zapcc memory consumption was very large, but I would have not have
expected something so critical. Another feature that would be interesting in
zapcc would be to set a max memory hard limit for the server instead of simply
a limit on the cache they are able to keep in memory. This would prevent hanging
the complete computer when something goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a good surprise with clang that was actually faster than GCC and also able
to work with four threads in parallel. This was not the case with previous
version of clang. On ETL, it is still significantly slower than GCC though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I'll continue using clang on this DLL project and use zapcc only on my
ETL project. I'll also focus on improving the compilation time on this project
and make it reasonable again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>clang</category><category>compiler</category><category>dll</category><category>gcc</category><category>projects</category><category>zapcc</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/03/disappointing-zapcc-performance-on-deep-learning-library-dll.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 12:41:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Release of zapcc 1.0 - Fast C++ compiler</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/03/release-zapcc-10-fast-cpp-compiler.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you remember, I recently wrote about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/12/zapcc-cpp-compilation-speed-against-gcc-54-and-clang-39.html"&gt;zapcc C++ compilation speed against gcc 5.4 and clang 3.9&lt;/a&gt; in which I was comparing the beta version of zapcc against gcc and clang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just been informed that zapcc was just released in version 1.0. I though it
was a good occasion to test it again. It will be compared against gcc-4.9,
gcc-5.3 and clang-3.9. This version is based on the trunk of clang-5.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I will use my Expression Template Library (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/etl/"&gt;ETL&lt;/a&gt;) project. This is a purely header-only
library with lots of templates. I'm going to compile the full test cases. This
is a perfect example for long compilation times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current tests are made on the last version of the library and with slightly
different parameters for compilation, therefore the absolute times are not
comparable, but the speedups should be comparable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like last time, I have configured zapcc to let is use 2Go RAM per caching
server, which is the maximum allowed. Moreover, I killed the servers before each
tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="debug-results"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Debug results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a debug build, with no optimizations enabled. Every build will
use four threads. This is the equivalent of doing make -j4 debug/bin/etl_test
without the link step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="73%"&gt;
&lt;col width="27%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-4.9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;190.09s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-5.3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200.92s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang++-3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;313.85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;81.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.86&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC-5.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC-4.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speedups are even more impressive than last time! zapcc is &lt;strong&gt;almost four
times fast than clang-3.9&lt;/strong&gt; and around &lt;strong&gt;2.5 times faster than GCC-5.3&lt;/strong&gt;.
Interestingly, we can see that gcc-5.3 is slighly slower than GCC-4.9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that they have the compiler even faster!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="release-results"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Release results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look now how the results are looking with optimizations enabled. Again,
every build will use four threads. This is the equivalent of doing make -j4
release_debug/bin/etl_test without the link step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="75%"&gt;
&lt;col width="25%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-4.9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;252.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-5.3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;264.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang++-3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;361.65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;237.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC-5.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC-4.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that this time the speedups are not as interesting as they were.
Very interestingly, it's the compiler that suffers the more from the
optimization overhead. Indeed, zapcc is three times slower in release mode than
it was in debug mode. Nevertheless, it still manages to beat the three other
compilers, by about 10% for Gcc and 50% than clang, which is already
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, we have observed that zapcc is always faster than the three
compilers tested in this experiment. Moreover, in debug mode, the speedups are
very significant, it was almost 4 times faster than clang and around 2.5 faster
than gcc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't seen any problem with the tool, it's like clang and it should generate
code of the same performance, but just compile it much faster. One problem
I have with zapcc is that it is not based on an already released version of
clang but on the trunk. That means it is hard to be compare with the exact same
version of clang and it is also a risk of running into clang bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the prices have not been published yet, it is indicated on the website
that zapcc is free for non-commercial entities. Which is really great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more information, you can go to the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.zapcc.com/"&gt;official website of zapcc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>clang</category><category>compiler</category><category>etl</category><category>gcc</category><category>projects</category><category>zapcc</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/03/release-zapcc-10-fast-cpp-compiler.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 13:50:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>zapcc C++ compilation speed against gcc 5.4 and clang 3.9</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/12/zapcc-cpp-compilation-speed-against-gcc-54-and-clang-39.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A week ago, I compared the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/11/zapcc-a-faster-cpp-compiler.html"&gt;compilation time performance of zapcc against gcc-4.9.3 and clang-3.7&lt;/a&gt;. On debug builds, zapcc was about 2 times faster than gcc and 3 times faster than clang. In this post, I'm going to try some more recent compilers, namely gcc 5.4 and clang 3.9 on the same project. If you want more information on zapcc, read the previous posts, this post will concentrate on results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I use my Expression Template Library
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/etl/"&gt;ETL&lt;/a&gt;). This is a purely header-only
library with lots of templates. I'm going to compile the full test cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the two articles are not directly comparable, since they were
obtained on two different computers. The one on which the present results are
done has a less powerful and only 16Go of RAM compared to the 32Go of RAM of my
build machine. Also take into account that that the present results were
obtained on a Desktop machine, there can be some perturbations from background
tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like on the previous results, it does not help using more threads than
physical cores, therefore, the results were only computed on up to 4 cores on
this machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link time is not taken into account on the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="debug-build"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Debug build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the result of the debug build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="55%"&gt;
&lt;col width="15%"&gt;
&lt;col width="15%"&gt;
&lt;col width="15%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-5.4.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;469s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;230s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;130s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang++-3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;710s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;371s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;218s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;214s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;112s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;66s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.05&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are almost the same as the previous test. zapcc is 3.3 times faster
to compile than Clang and around 2 times faster than GCC. It seems that GCC 5.4
is a bit faster than GCC 4.9.3 while clang 3.9 is a bit slower than clang 3.7,
but nothing terribly significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, for debug builds, zapcc can bring a very significant improvement to
your compile times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="release-build"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Release build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see what is the status of Release builds. Since the results are comparable
between the numbers of threads, the results here are just for one thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more time consuming since a lot of optimizations are enabled and more
features from ETL are enabled as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="79%"&gt;
&lt;col width="21%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-5.4.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;782s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang++-3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;960s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;640s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a release build, the speedups are much less interesting. Nevertheless, they
are still significant. zapcc is still 1.2 times faster than gcc and 1.5 times
faster than clang. Then speedup against clang 3.9 is significantly higher than
it was on my experiment with clang 3.7, it's possible that clang 3.9 is slower
or simply has new optimization passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous conclusion still holds with modern version of compilers: zapcc is
much faster than other compilers on Debug builds of template heavy code. More
than 3 times faster than clang-3.9 and about 2 times faster than gcc-5.4. Since
it's based on clang, there should not be any issue compiling projects that
already compile with a recent clang. Even though the speedups are less
interesting on a release build, it is still significantly, especially compared
against clang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm really interested in finding out what will be the pricing for zapcc once
out of the beta or if they will be able to get even faster!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the comparison with gcc 4.9.3 and clang 3.7, you can have a look at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/11/zapcc-a-faster-cpp-compiler.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more information about zapcc, you can go to the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.zapcc.com/"&gt;official website of zapcc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>clang</category><category>compiler</category><category>etl</category><category>gcc</category><category>meta</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/12/zapcc-cpp-compilation-speed-against-gcc-54-and-clang-39.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 17:46:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>zapcc - a faster C++ compiler</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/11/zapcc-a-faster-cpp-compiler.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update: For a comparison against more modern compiler versions, you can read: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/12/zapcc-cpp-compilation-speed-against-gcc-54-and-clang-39.html"&gt;zapcc C++ compilation speed against gcc 5.4 and clang 3.9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just joined the private beta program of zapcc. Zapcc is a c++ compiler, based
on Clang which aims at being much faster than other C++ compilers. How they are
doing this is using a caching server that saves some of the compiler structures,
which should speed up compilation a lot. The private beta is free, but once the
compiler is ready, it will be a commercial compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every C++ developer knows that compilation time can quickly be an issue when
programs are getting very big and especially when working with template-heavy
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To benchmark this new compiler, I use my Expression Template Library
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/etl/"&gt;ETL&lt;/a&gt;). This is a purely header-only
library with lots of templates. There are lots of test cases which is what I'm
going to compile. I'm going to compare against Clang-3.7 and gcc-4.9.3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have configured zapcc to let is use 2Go RAM per caching server, which is the
maximum allowed. Moreover, I killed the servers before each tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="debug-build"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Debug build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a debug build. In that configuration, there is no optimization
going on and several of the features of the library (GPU, BLAS, ...) are
disabled. This is the fastest way to compile ETL. I gathered this result on
a 4 core, 8 threads, Intel processor, with an SSD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following table presents the results with different number of threads and
the difference of zapcc compared to the other compilers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="42%"&gt;
&lt;col width="11%"&gt;
&lt;col width="13%"&gt;
&lt;col width="11%"&gt;
&lt;col width="11%"&gt;
&lt;col width="11%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-4.9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;350s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;185s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;104s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;91s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang++-3.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;513s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;271s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;153s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;145s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;138s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;158s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;87s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;47s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;44s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;42s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.103&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is pretty clear! zapcc is around &lt;strong&gt;three times faster than Clang&lt;/strong&gt; and around
&lt;strong&gt;two times faster than GCC&lt;/strong&gt;. This is pretty impressive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those that think than Clang is always faster than GCC, keep in mind that
this is not the case for template-heavy code such as this library. In all my
tests, Clang has always been slower and much memory hungrier than GCC on
template-heavy C++ code. And sometimes the difference is very significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, we can also see that going past the physical cores is not really
interesting on this computer. On some computer, the speedups are interesting,
but not on this one. Always benchmark!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="release-build"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Release build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen the results on a debug build, let's now compare on something a bit
more timely, a release build with all options of ETL enabled (GPU, BLAS, ...),
which should make it significantly longer to compile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="40%"&gt;
&lt;col width="12%"&gt;
&lt;col width="12%"&gt;
&lt;col width="12%"&gt;
&lt;col width="12%"&gt;
&lt;col width="12%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;-j8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;g++-4.9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;628s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;336s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;197s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;184s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;clang++-3.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;663s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;388s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;215s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;212s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;205s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;zapcc++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;515s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;281s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;173s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;168s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;158s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS Clang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.38&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Speedup VS GCC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, we can see that the difference is much lower. Zapcc is &lt;strong&gt;between 1.2
and 1.4 times faster than Clang&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;between 1.1 and 1.3 times faster than
GCC&lt;/strong&gt;. This shows that most of the speedups from zapcc are in the front end of
the compiler. This is not a lot but still significant over long builds,
especially if you have few threads where the absolute difference would be
higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also observe that Clang is now almost on par with GCC which shows that
optimization is faster in Clang while front and backend is faster in gcc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also have to keep in mind that zapcc memory usage is higher than Clang
because of all the caching. Moreover, the server are still up in between
compilations, so this memory usage stays between builds, which may not be what
you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for runtime, I have not seen any significant difference in performance
between the clang version and the zapcc. According to the official benchmarks
and documentation, there should not be any difference in that between zapcc and
the version of clang on which zapcc is based.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="incremental-build"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Incremental build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, zapcc should shine at incremental building, but I was unable to show
any speedup when changing a single without killing the zapcc servers. Maybe
I did something wrong in my usage of zapcc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we can see that zapcc is always faster than both GCC and Clang,
on my template-heavy library. Moreover, on debug builds, it is much faster than
any of the two compilers, being more than 2 times faster than GCC and more than
3 times faster than clang. This is really great. Moreover, I have not seen any
issue with the tool so far, it can seamlessly replace Clang without problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a bit weird that you cannot allocate more than 2Go to the zapcc servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a program, that's really impressive. I hope that they are continuing the
good work and especially that this motivates other compilers to improve the
speed of compilation (especially of templates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more information, you can go to the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.zapcc.com/"&gt;official website of zapcc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>clang</category><category>compiler</category><category>etl</category><category>gcc</category><category>projects</category><category>zapcc</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/11/zapcc-a-faster-cpp-compiler.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 12:17:50 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>