<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>@Blog("Baptiste Wicht") (Hardware)</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" href="http://wichtounet.github.io/categories/hardware.xml" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2014 18:26:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola &lt;http://getnikola.com/&gt;</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Home Server Adventure – Step 3</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2014/01/home-server-adventure-step-3.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are some news about my &lt;a title="Home Server Adventure – Step 2" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/08/home-server-adventure-step-2/"&gt;home server installation project&lt;/a&gt;.In the past, I already installed a server in a custom Norco case. I wanted to replace my QNAP NAS with a better server, the QNAP being too slow and not extensible enough for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is it how it looks right now (sorry about the photo qualitiy :( my phone does not seem to focus anymore...):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/asdf1.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2653" alt="My Home Rack of Server" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/asdf1-168x300.png" width="168" height="300"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; My Home Rack of Server&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.5em;"&gt;So I replaced my QNAP NAS with a custom-built NAS. Again, I bought a NORCO case, the RPC-4220. This case has 20 SATA/SAS bays. I bought it with a replacement of the SAS backplane by a SATA one. I also ordered some fan replacement to make it less noisy. I installed my 6 hard disk in Raid 5, managed with mdadm, with LVM partitions on top of the array. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added an APC UPS which allows me to go through all the minor power issues that there is in my old apartment and which also me about 10 minutes of backup when there is a power outage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't added a lot of services on the server. I now run Owncloud on the server and that completely replaces my Dropbox account. I also improved by Sabnzbd installation with other newsgroup automation tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not directly related to my rack, but I also installed a custom XBMC server for my TV. It reads from the NAS server. And of course, it runs Gentoo too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, I'll add a new simple server as a front firewall to manage security a bit more than here and avoid having to configure redirection in my shitty router (which I would like to replace, but there are not a lot of compatible rack router for my ISP unfortunately). It will probably use a Norco case too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any question about my build, don't hesitate ;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Server</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2014/01/home-server-adventure-step-3.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 13:05:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Server Adventure - Step 2</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/08/home-server-adventure-step-2.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you remember, I talked about &lt;a title="Home Server Adventure – Step 1" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1/"&gt;my home server project&lt;/a&gt; in a previous post. I had installed an old Dell Poweredge server, a 3com gigabit switch and a monitoring console. The problem with this configuration was that it was too noisy as the rack is installed in my apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did was to &lt;a title="ZyXEL GS1910-24 Managed Gigabit Switch Review" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/zyxel-gs1910-managed-gigabit-switch-review/"&gt;replace my old 3Com switch with a Zyxel managed fanless switch&lt;/a&gt;. Being fanless, this switch is completely silent which makes a good difference :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I have replaced the Dell server with &lt;a title="Norco RPC 230 Case Review" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/08/norco-rpc-230-case-review/"&gt;a custom installation in a Norco-RPC 230 case&lt;/a&gt;. The basic case comes with two 80mm fans in the front. These two fans are very powerful, but they are quite noisy. I replaced them with two Enermax T.B. Silence 80mm fans. They are almost silent, it is really great. It is probably not enough airflow for a large configuration, but in my case, I think that this will be largely enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've already installed several services on my server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 16px;"&gt;Tiny Tiny RSS: a web-based news feed reader and aggregator. I use it to replace Feedly which I was getting less and less fond to. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sabnzbd: I already had this NZB download on my desktop, but now as it is on the server, it can download even when I'm not at home.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Zabbix: a monitoring application that manages all my appliances and server (the new server, the NAS, the switch and the router). It is my first attempt with Zabbix. It is a bit cryptic to conigure, but the features are very numerous.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Teamspeak and Mumble: They already were installed on the previous server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to install new services on the future, but I have no plans for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of the rack in its current state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-23-15.31.45.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2610" alt='19" Rack' src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-23-15.31.45-168x300.jpg" width="168" height="300"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 19" Rack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also installed my router and the NAS on a layer in the rack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't see it, but I have also added to rackable PDU on the back to have to organize a bit the cables. Even if it still not perfect, it is already better than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I think that my system in in good shape. When I will have some more budget, I will replace QNAP NAS with a custom server, probably again with a Norco case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Server</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/08/home-server-adventure-step-2.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:16:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Norco RPC 230 Case Review</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/08/norco-rpc-230-case-review.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As my previous Dell 1U server was &lt;a title="Home Server Adventure – Step 1" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1/"&gt;too noisy for my home server installation&lt;/a&gt;. I invested in a case, a Norco RPC 230 model. This case is a 2U standard case for 19" rack. It supports micro-ATX motherboard and ATX power supply. These components are easy too find, so that makes it a very interesting case for a home server installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the case at &lt;a title="Ri-Vier Automatisering" href="https://ri-vier.eu/"&gt;Ri-Vier Automatisering&lt;/a&gt;, which is the Norco european distributor. I directly ordered it with the RL-26 rails for the rack and the ATX power supply that is provided by Ri-Vier. For the case, I also bought a micro-ATX Gigabyte G41M-Combo motherboard. I already had 4GB of DDR2 RAM and a Core 2 Duo processor from a previous configuration. I also took my old 120GB Samung SSD for this server. This would be largely sufficient for what I plan to run on this server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case has four 3.5" drive bays and one 5.25" drive bay. The air flow is provided with two 80mm fans on the front panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Package&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received the package very quickly from Ri-Vier. The case is packaged in double box and everything in the package is well ordered. The power supply was already in the box itself. Here is a picture of the content of the package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.45.14.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2596" alt="2013-08-20 09.45.14" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.45.14-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It contains only the case and the necessary screws. The rails are not on this picture, since I already had installed them in my rack. As you see, there are no manual, which may be a bit frustrating. Once you remove the top panel (4 screws to remove), you can see the inside of the case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.54.09.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2595" alt="2013-08-20 09.54.09" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.54.09-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the top are the four bays for the drives. They are removable. As you can see on the picture, the power supply has plenty of cables. I would have expected a power supply with less cables to come with this case as there is not much room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a view of the front panel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.22.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2593" alt="2013-08-20 11.11.22" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.22-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two USB ports on the front, the Power and Reset buttons as well as LEDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even without any manual, the installation is fairly easy. The top panel can be removed by unscrewing 4 four screws on the side. I strongly recommend to remove the 4 drive bays before installing the other components to make some room. Once it is done, the motherboard can be screwed in place. The power supply is attached by four screws on the back panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed a SSD 2.5" in the leftmost disk bay. I had some issues with this installation as the bays do not have any screws on the side, only on the bottom. They are really not made for anything else than 3.5" drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of my installation once finished:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.39.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2592" alt="2013-08-20 11.11.39" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.39-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to make it looks nice with the cables, but only because I have not installed any CD-Rom, so I did put a lot of cables in its place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it is done, I have installed it in my rack. It is not straightforward without a manual, but I was able to screw it to the rails. I did put two screws on each side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.08.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2591" alt="2013-08-20 11.31.08" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.08-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in place, it looks quite good:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.51.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2590" alt="2013-08-20 11.31.51" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.51-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I don't know if I have done something wrong, but the rails are not sliding smoothly, they are blocking at two places and the last part is quite hard to push. Anyway, as I won't be moving it a lot, I think it is ok. You also have to remember that even if it is a short depth case, the RL-26 rails are not short at all, they are not made for short depth racks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it is launched, the server is quite busy due to the two 80mm fans. However, the airflow is quite strong, which is what most customers want. It is still more silent than my Dell server, but not enough for a home experience. I will try to replace them with more silent fans in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pros&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;Enough bays for a simple server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support standard formats&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Enough air flow&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Very short depth&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Seems of heavy duty construction&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Looks nice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Not too expensive&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Should fit in most racks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;No manuals at all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Disk bays not very convenient&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The provided power supply is not very adapted to the case.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The provided rails seems to not slide smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, I would say that this case is very fit to a custom installation as all the components are standards. I would recommend it for a similar usage than mine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Review</category><category>Server</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/08/norco-rpc-230-case-review.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 08:38:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ZyXEL GS1910-24 Managed Gigabit Switch Review</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/07/zyxel-gs1910-managed-gigabit-switch-review.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A short time ago, &lt;a title="Home Server Adventure – Step 1" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1/"&gt;I decided to install servers in a rack at my home&lt;/a&gt;. Although working very well, my 3Com managed was too much noisy for being at home. That is why I decided to change it for fanless switch. After some research, I finally chose a ZyXEL GS1910-24. It is a web-manageable gigabit switch. I chose the 24 ports version. This version has also 4 SFPs that replace 4 normal ports if enabled. I don't think I will ever need the SFPs, but it is nice to know that there are here if necessary. This switch has a lot of cool features, it supports IPV6, QoS, VLANs, filtering, RADIUS and so on.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;The package&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package does not contains a lot of things, but does contain the essential:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;The switch itself&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A power code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rack mounting brackets and screws&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Manuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture on the package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-16.51.47.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2574" alt="2013-07-11 16.51.47" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-16.51.47-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch is really small, twice narrower than my 3Com switch and more than twice lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing special to say about the package, it is neatly done and has everything that is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation inside a rack is really easy. Each bracket is mounted with 4 screws onto the switch and then two screws are holding each bracket into place in the rack. Here is a picture of the rack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-17.07.00.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2575" alt="2013-07-11 17.07.00" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-17.07.00-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you put the power cord, it directly starts up and everything already works fine. The state of each port is represented by a led. Orange indicates a 100Mbit/s connection while green indicates 1Gbit/s connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch does not make a single noise and does not vibrate, it is really good&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to configure the switch is to use the web configurator. By default, the switch IP is 192.168.1.1. As my router had the same IP, I had to disable it temporarily before changing the IP of the switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web configuration is very complete, you can change absolutely everything from here. You have also access to a lot of monitoring tools from here. The most useful being of course the port monitoring interface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Screenshot-from-2013-07-11-172745.png"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2576" alt="Port Monitoring" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Screenshot-from-2013-07-11-172745-300x132.png" width="300" height="132"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend changing the default IP address and the server password as first things on the switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't make the list of everything that is configurable on this switch, but the list is pretty impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm really impressed by this switch. The switch is highly configurable and seems to perfectly fit my need. I would totally recommend this switch for rack installation at home. You can also totally use it as a desktop switch if you needs for a big switch on your desktop too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Network</category><category>Review</category><category>Server</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/07/zyxel-gs1910-managed-gigabit-switch-review.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 08:38:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Server Adventure - Step 1</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years now, I've almost always had a server running at home. First it was an old desktop computer and then it was a QNAP NAS. The problem with the QNAP is that it is not fast at all and not as flexible as I would like it to be. Moreover, I was also running a Teamspeak server on my desktop for when my friends and I were playing together. So I decided to first install a simple server to replace my teamspeak server and I would services of my NAS with my new server. But this time, I decided to go for the complete option: A 19" rack :)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Hardware&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I bought all I needed to install my 19" rack at home. I bought everything already used on auctions on Ricardo/Anibis (Switzerland Ebay equivalents) and Ebay. Here is what I got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;A 19" inch rack with 40 HE of the mark GURTNER + SCHNIEPP AG&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A old Dell Poweredge 1850 server&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A 8-ports Compaq KVM switch&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A monitor/keyboard console for administrating the servers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A 3Com managed Gigabit switch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got that for less than 500$. It is probably possible to get a similar configuration for less than that in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some pictures (sorry for the poor quality):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-05-17.58.322.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2568" alt="2013-07-05 17.58.32" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-05-17.58.322-576x1024.jpg" width="576" height="1024"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-05-17.59.232.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2567" alt="2013-07-05 17.59.23" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-05-17.59.232-576x1024.jpg" width="576" height="1024"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, it is kind of empty. I will also put my NAS and my internet provider router in the rack in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A this time, the cables are not very good organized, I will try to purchase some guides to make that look better and I will also try to find a rack PDU to distribute power without cables everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also need to find two 120mm fans for the top of my case to improve air circulation. Very quiet 120mm can be found, so noise won't be a problem I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, I also plan to find an UPS, but they are very expensive, so I will continue looking at auctions for them. The problem being that the battery should not be too old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Software&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I've installed Gentoo on the server. At first, I wanted to install a Gentoo Hardened distribution with Selinux, but it turned out that it was too much of a hassle. After more than 10 hours of trying to make it work, I started again and in less than two hours my Gentoo installation was working. I will probably try again in the future, at least to harden the server and I hope it will go with less problems. The server is of course gui-less, only console access is more than sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now on, I have only a Teamspeak server and a Mumble server installed on the server, but I plan to add new services on it, Sabnzb for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also installed iptables to add some layer of protection, even if I don't think that it is necessary in my case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I used dyndns to map my public ip to a domain name to make it easier to reach. For now, I haven't installed an update client, but I plan to try ddclient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Problems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made some mistake when choosing the components for my installation. First of all, they are too noisy. The server and the switch are a real problem. They are both made for professional installations. Generally 1U server have very small fans (40mm generally) which are very noisy. So I decided to upgrade my configurations with two changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;I will buy a fanless switch, probably unmanaged. They are plenty of very good fanless switches, even managed one for a reasonable price. I will try to first find a used one on auction, but I may consider buying a new one, as there exists some for about a hundred dollars. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I will replace the Dell server with a custom server. I found some very good cases made by Norco. I'll buy a Micro ATX motherboard and install my old computer configuration (&lt;a title="Why and how I completely left Windows for Linux" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/why-how-left-windows-for-linux/"&gt;the one I had before&lt;/a&gt;) on it. It won't cost too much I think, although much more than the 30$ Dell server I have now ;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other problem being that the Dell server is too deep for my rack, so I can't close the back part as you can see on the pictures, but replacing it with the Norco case will solve the problem :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound crazy to have a complete rack at home, but I thing that it is a great way to experience with servers and network. It is also quite practical if you plan to have several servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to post some posts on the subject on the future, so I hope  that it interests some people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Network</category><category>Server</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 09:02:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardware Guide : The power supply</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/09/hardware-guide-the-power-supply.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After writing a lot about Java concurrency, I wanted to write about something else, I chosen Hardware, so I wrote a new guide about power supplies.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power supply provide electrical power to the computer and to the several components. Without power supply, a computer cannot start. The power supply is connected to the power distribution system of your home and convert this power into the good number of watts needed by the components of your PC. All the power is redistributed using several different connectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we buy a power supply, you need to keep in mind several elements, the available connectors and the power generated by the power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Connectors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From your power supply, several connectors go out. All of these connectors have a specific use. Here are the existing types of connectors that you can find on a power supply :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ATX Connectors&lt;/strong&gt; : This connector is used to power the motherboard. Generally, there is 20 pins, but new motherboards need 24. So new power supplies provide a 24 pins connectors with 4 pins detachable. Pay attention that some motherboard also needs an additional 4 pins connector, so verify that your power supply has this  connector before buying it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molex Connectors for  5 ¼ et 3 ½ peripheral&lt;/strong&gt; : This connector power an IDE component (hard disk, CD/DVD reader/writer).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molex Connectors for  floppy&lt;/strong&gt; : this connector is less and less used so not all power supply provide this connector.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12V 6 pins Connector&lt;/strong&gt; : This connector enable to connect a PCI-Express graphics card. Not all cards need that connector, only the last generation graphics card need a power addition. Most of the graphics card have a connector of this type, but for big configuration with two graphics card (SLI or CrossFire), you'll need two connectors. The power supply with two connectors of this type are named SLI-Ready.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SATA Connectors&lt;/strong&gt; : To power SATA peripheral.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally each type of connector have keyed to avoid branch the cable in the wrong direction. There is also adapters to switch from one type to an other one or to double a connector (but pay attention to not overhead your power supply).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay also attention to the length of the cables if you have a big case (Big Tower).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The power&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of your power supply is the number of Watts that it can deliver. Pay attention that a basic power supply will often have brownouts if there is a lot of load. This is why it's more interesting to choose a known power supply with a lower tension than a noname one with a bigger tension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention to the tension on each connector. Some alimentations don't provide the indicated tension. It's why, it's always good to find tests of clients on Internet before buying something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you need enough power for your components. The components needing the more power is the processor and the graphics cards. The other components needs less power. For a basic computer a power supply of 300W is enough. When we use last generation graphics card or dual/quadri core processor, you need to have more power, almost 400W-450W. When you have several processors or graphics card, there is a lot more. There is power supply with 1000W but this is an exception only needed (not always...) by big gamers or scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To compute the number of Watt that a component need, you can almost use this list :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour calculer le besoin en Watts d'un composant vous pouvez plus ou moins vous fier à cette liste :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Motherboard : 40-50 W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Simple core processor : 40-50 W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dual Core processor : 90-100 W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Server Processor (Xeon by example) : ~150W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Graphics card PCI/AGP : 50 W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Graphics card PCI Express : 125W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Additional PCI Card : 15-55 W&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Hard Disk : 15-40 W depending on the use&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;CD/DVD Readers/Writers : 10-20 W&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these datas can change from one peripheral to an other, but this is a good mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use &lt;a title="PSU Calculator" href="http://www.extreme.outervision.com/psucalculatorlite.jsp" target="_blank"&gt;this online calculator&lt;/a&gt; to compute the power you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Standards&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to choose the power supply in terms of the standard of your computer case. An ATX power supply doesn't fit an case of type Micro-ATX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Noise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power supply is an element who heats a lot, so you need a cooling system. Generally a power supply have a fan, but some power supply use a passive cooling system. The better is to have a big fan (120mm), it makes less noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also use a power supply with two fans for a better air extraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention that the fans are the most silent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Modularity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some power supply are modular. This power supplies don't have the connectors directly connected to the box, but you can connect them yourself. So we only connect the connectors we need. This improve the air flow. But these models are more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Size&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some power supplies are bigger than the other, so pay attention that it fits in your case. This the case for the most powerful models and some modular models. It can also be hard to put some power supplies in some cases due to their concept. To be sure that the two are compatibles, you can directly contact your vendor or make a search on the internet to have returns on the mount of this power supply on your case. But generally you will not have compatibility problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Power Consumption&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more vendors put the power consumption on the front of the stage. So it's interesting to choose a power supply with less power consumption if you have the choice between several power supplies that are in your needs. There is some standards like the Certification 80 plus that guarantee that the efficiency of the power supply is at least of 80%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, the choice of a power supply is not really serious, but it's a serious point in a configuration. Pay attention to have a power supply with enough connectors and enough power to power all your components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Tips&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some rules to choose a good power supply :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Don't use too much connectors splitters, you risk to overload your power supply&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Clean regularly your power supply. Don't let the dust win. The fan can block and don't correctly evacuate the heating and the components can be broken. Of course, this is also a good thing to do for the computer in general.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Don't use a power supply in a configuration where the components needs more power than the power supply provide. If you make it you can stress the power supply and the different connectors will not provide enough tension and some of your components may not appreciate this situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Others</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/09/hardware-guide-the-power-supply.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2010 07:33:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to choose a monitor for your computer ?</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/06/how-to-choose-a-monitor.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The monitor is a very important part of your computer. Indeed without it you cannot display anything. There is several types of monitors and the price varying a lot. The most limiting criteria will be your budget when you've to choose a new monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we'll see what to watch before buying a new monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h5&gt;1. Type&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is several types of monitors :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CRT Monitor&lt;/strong&gt; : This is the old type of monitor. They were a lot bigger than the current monitors. That type is no longer being sold.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LCD Monitor&lt;/strong&gt; :  This is the most common type of monitor actually, a lot smaller and lighter than CRT. It works with liquid crystals.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LED Monitor&lt;/strong&gt; : Recent technology using LED. This kind of monitor is a LCD monitor that use a LED backlight. The image is a bit better than with LCD and you'll have a better contrast. The life time of a LED monitor is better than LCD and the power consumption is also lower. And you can find very thin monitor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the norm is the LCD monitors. The CRT doesn't have any advantages versus the LCD. Depending on your budget, you'll have to choose between LCD and LED, a bit more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;2. Size&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing we watch when buying a monitor is of course its size, in inches. The size of a computer monitor is between 15" and 30". Bigger the monitor is better the resolution it can display is. With a 22" you can by example watch 2 A4 pages side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common size today is 19" and you'll find that kind of monitor from 150$. I think it's a good start to buy a least a 19" monitor. Today, it's not interesting to buy a smaller monitor. You will also find 20" monitors at almost the same prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you watch a lot of films on your computer or playing games, I advice you to choose 22" or 24" moniors. You can find them from 200$ to 400$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take care that big monitor, like 30", needs a big graphics card and often needs the DVI Dual Link technology. It seems that you need two cables to connect your monitor but only one port on your graphics card. This technology allows to display very high resolution using two TMDS transmitters on one cable. So be sure that your graphics cards supports DVI Dual Link before buying 30" monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll also have to pay attention to the resolution of your monitor. Indeed there is 19" monitor that only displays 1024x768 resolution instead of the normal 1280x1024. Here are the recommended resolutions for several sizes :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;15" : 1024*768 on 4:3&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;17" : 1280*1024 on 4:3 and 1440*900 on 16:10&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;19" : 1280*1024 on 4:3 and 1440*900 on 16:10&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;20" : 1600*1200 on 4:3 and 1680*1050 on 16:10&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;22" : 1680*1050 on 16:10&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;24" : 1920*1200 on 16:10&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;30" : 2560*1600 on 16:10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than the sizes and the resolutions, you can also pay attention to the format of the monitor :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4/3&lt;/strong&gt; : This is the "normal" format of the monitor.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16/9&lt;/strong&gt; : This is the wide format of monitor. The resolution will be by example 1280x720 or 1366x768. This is the base resolution for a lot of video stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16/10 &lt;/strong&gt;: This format is also a wide format. The constructors prefer sometimes to use 16/10 instead of 16/9, because the resolutions are better and easier to build. If you watch video in 16/9 format with this monitor you'll have black band but the same size of video. This monitor is also better for gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can, take a wide monitor. I found it a lot better to work on, play videos and play games. Personnally, I prefer 16/10 but if you play only videos, take a 16/9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;3. Response time&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very important criteria is the response time, mainly for the gamers. This is the time, in milliseconds, that take the monitor to put a pixel from white to black. If you do only office work, this criteria is not important. But for the gamers, it's an other problems. In fact, with a high response time, you may have a blurring effect due to changes too fast for the monitor. It's why I advice to take monitors with 5ms or less for gamers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;4. LCD Panel Technology&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is several types of LCD panels :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TN : &lt;/strong&gt;This is the fastest and cheapest panel. But the viewing angle is not the best and the colors are not optimal. The color schema is only coded with 6 bits, so it cannot display the full color schema of the operating system. It uses dithering to display all colors but that put some swarming effects on the display when there is a lot of moves. This type of panel is for the big FPS gamers, the low budget and for the office worker.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VA&lt;/strong&gt; : This is the most polyvalent panels. The color scheme is 8 bits. The response time is higher than TN, but we've some good monitors. This is a bit more expensive than TN. This is a good panel for persons who play games and play videos.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IPS&lt;/strong&gt; : This is the panels with the better viewing angle, also with a color schema of 8 bits. This is the best panels for the video and photos. The response time of IPS is lowering this last times, so you can find IPS panels with 5ms of response time. So it's interesting also for gamers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To resume, if you search the best prices or the best response time, use a TN panels. If you want a multipurpose monitors, take a MVA and if you do a lot of photo/video edition, choose a IPS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last times, the differences between the panels are reduced, so don't block your choice on a type of panel, compare different monitors with different panels type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;5. Brightness / Contrast&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are two others important criterias to choose a monitor. Start with the brightness. This defines the visibility of a monitor in a very enlightened environment and is calculated in candela by square meter (cd/m²). This is not the most import criteria, but I think a minimum is 250 cd/m².&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contrast is more import than the brightness, in my point of view. This is the difference between the brightest point and the darkest point of the monitor. More the constrast is, more the colors are good. The minimum is 500:1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention to the fact that the displayed contrast is sometimes dynamic and not real. The dynamic contrast is computed with numerical modifications of the images with a software in the monitors. This contrast is not a good as the real monitors and the numbers are to take with care. The real contrast is the best criteria. So take only the dynamic contrast as a second criteria to compare monitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;6. Others&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that we don't consider at this time is a multi-monitor configuration. With the recent graphics cards it's really easy to put several monitors on your computers. This allows you to display several things at the same time. For a developer, it's really useful. It can see it's code in a monitor and the result in an other monitor or documentation on the second monitor. It works also with games, the game on a screen and your playlist on an other. If you've the budget, it's a very interesting things to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the connectors, the recent monitors have DVI connectors and sometimes HDMI (HD connector). There is still several old monitors with VGA connectors, but avoid them and prefer DVI connectors. DVI have better performances than VGA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some monitors allows you to switch from landspace to portrait . So you can change mode depending on what you're doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay also attention to the guarantee you've with the monitors. You can find 0 pixel warranty during x months, that can be interesting with expensive monitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An argument that the sellers give you is the HD labels. There is several labels :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatible HD&lt;/strong&gt; : This label doesn't give you the ability to read videos in high definition but only that a HD video can be read but converted in a standard format. This label must be avoided.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HD Ready&lt;/strong&gt; : This label needs a resolution of at least 720 lignes and a 16/9 format. You can see your videos in high defintion but this label doesnt guarantee that the image will not modified so you can have a less good quality.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full HD&lt;/strong&gt; : This label needs a resolution of at least 1080 lines. This is the best label for HD videos. But it is not certified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I advice you to take a monitors with the Full HD monitors but take also cares that the monitor characteristic are good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The viewing angle can also be interesting. This define at how much degrees you can still watch the monitors with a good quality. This angle is calculated vertically and horizontally. The interest of the viewing angle is strongly depending on your usage of your monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also see glossy monitors. The colors and the contrast are a little bit better than matte but the reflects are a lot more disturbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;7. Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, the first thing to consider is the size of the monitor and the usage we'll have with this monitor. And after that we can take care of the details to compare the different monitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personnally, I have two 24" monitors. This is awesome to work, develop, play games and videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a developer, I can strongly recommend to take big wide monitors (22" or 24" inches wide) and if you've the budget, two monitors will be really comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that these advices will help you to choose the good monitors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Hardware</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/06/how-to-choose-a-monitor.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2010 06:42:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Links of the Week</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/04/links-of-the-week-2.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are some interesting links of this week :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2010/04/three-monitors-for-every-user.html" target="_blank"&gt;Three Monitors for Every User&lt;/a&gt; : Jeff Atwood explain how to works with three monitors on the same computers and what that give to the user.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/library/j-ce/index.html" target="_blank"&gt;Tip: When you can't throw an exception&lt;/a&gt; : Elliotte Rusty Harold explore solutions on how to works with exceptions in public APIs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blogs.sun.com/tor/entry/leak_unit_tests" target="_blank"&gt;How to Write a Memory Leak Unit Test&lt;/a&gt; : Tor Norbye explain how to make unit test to verify for memory leak&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://agile.dzone.com/news/8-tips-performance-metrics"&gt;8 Tips for Performance Metrics&lt;/a&gt; by Jurgen Appelo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll find this links interesting. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Java</category><category>Links</category><category>Performances</category><category>Tests</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/04/links-of-the-week-2.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 06:34:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardware Guide : The memory chips</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/03/hardware-guide-memory.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;
The RAM memory (Random Access Memory) of a computer is used to stock data during their treatment. The operating system will load in memory the useful files and all the datas of the launched programs. Its necessary to have an adequate quantity of memory.
&lt;p&gt;The RAM has two important caracteristics :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Speed data access : The access to data in RAM is very fast, a lot more than access to hard disks. It's essential to give access to data in a quick way.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Volatility : The data doesn't remain in memory after computer shutdown. So this is not a storage device only a temporary data storage device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a computer doesn't have enough memory, the operating system will simulate virtual memory using the hard disks, but like said above, the access on the hard disk is a lot slower than memory and the performances of the system will decrease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is essential to make the good choice when choosing memory chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/memory_chip.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-194" title="Memory Chip" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/memory_chip-300x144.jpg" alt="Memory Chip" width="300" height="144"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;2. Size&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to define is the quantity of memory do you need. The minimum memory is 512 Mo, but the this will be just enough even in Windows XP and it's absolutely not enough for Windows Vista. For Windows Seven, you can have 512 Mo, but it will not be confortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thats why i will advise at least 1 Go of RAM, but better is 2 Go. After, you have also to see the used applications to estimate the needed memory size. If you need to do images/movies treatments or play recent games 2Go is necessary. If you use more than 3 Go of RAM, be sure that you operating system can support that. Only 64 bit operating system support more than 3 Go of RAM. Generally, the last motherboards use the Dual Channel technologies for memory chips. Namely we control the chips by pair to have better bandwith. With this technology, you must use 2 chips with the same caracterics (two same chips will be better). Some motherboards have Quad Channel technology support. This is the same as Dual Channel but for 4 chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motherboards have normally 4 memory locations. I advise to use only 2 for the start. This will make the update easier. It's not really useful to buy 4 chips of 512 Mo instead of 2 chips of 1 Go. The prices are almost the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--nextpage--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;3. Type&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is several types of memory with for each type several standards. Here are the 4 main types :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SDR-SDRAM&lt;/strong&gt; : This is an obsolete type of RAM, but you can still find it in very old computers. A chip had 168 pins and 2 keyways.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR-SDRAM&lt;/strong&gt; : This is an evolution of the SDR, with better frequencies. It has 184 pins and one keyway. It's not selled today and have been replaced by DDR2.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2-SDRAM&lt;/strong&gt; : This is the standard type of mmemory. All the new motherboards support this type. It has better frequencies. It has 240 pins.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-SDRAM&lt;/strong&gt; : Really recent technology and still almost few used. The motherboards support more and more that technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the main used chips are DDR2 and the new motherboards are all compatible with this norm. This is why, i'll advise to directly buy DDR2. If you want better performances use DDR3, but it's only necessary with big configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each technology there is several formats. This formats indicate the frequency of the chip. The DDR have a internal frequency and an external one. Here are the different formats :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 400&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-3200 : External Frequency (EF) : 200Mhz, Internal Frequency (IF) : 100Mhz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 533&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-4200 : EF : 266, IF : 133&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 667&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-5300 : EF : 333, IF : 166&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 800&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-6400 : EF : 400, IF : 200&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 1000&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-8000 : EF : 500, IF : 250&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 1066&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-8500 : EF : 533, IF : 266&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR2 1200&lt;/strong&gt; - PC2-10000 : EF : 600, IF : 300&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More the frequency is high, more the access to the data is fast. Nevertheless, like you will see in the next chapter, it's not enough to have a high frequency. In fact, a very high frequency has no utility with high latencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motherboard have also a frequency, so have to keep in mind to not decrease the performances of the memory with the motherboard and vice-versa. The motherboards doesn't support any formats, so you have to control the compatibility between the memory and the motherboard. More the frequency is high, more it will be costly. So have to choose the right middle between performances and price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; : Some mainboards have limitations on the supported number of chips of a certain type of chips. For example a mainboard XXX can support only three chips of type YYY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the persons that want to make overclocking, i will advise to take chips with very high frequencies (DDR2 1066 and superior). But for all that want a simple configuration, lower frequencies will be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the persons interested of the very high frequencies, here are the caracteristics of the DDR3 norm :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-800&lt;/strong&gt; : 100 MHz- 400 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-1066&lt;/strong&gt; : 133 MHz - 533 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-1333&lt;/strong&gt; : 166 MHz -à 667 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-1600&lt;/strong&gt; : 200 MHz - 800 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-1800&lt;/strong&gt; : 225 MHz - 900 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-1866&lt;/strong&gt; : 233 MHz - 933 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-2000&lt;/strong&gt; : 250 MHz - 1000 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-2133&lt;/strong&gt; : 266 MHz - 1066 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-2200&lt;/strong&gt; : 275 MHz - 1100 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DDR3-2300&lt;/strong&gt; : 287 MHz - 1150 MHz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To choose the DDR3 memory, the best criteria is the price. Take the format the most according to your budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. Synchronisation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An other caracteristic of memory is the number of clock cycles necessary to access a data. This caracteristic is represented by 4 numbers (x-x-x-x) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CAS&lt;/strong&gt; (Column Address Strobe) Delay or CAS Latency : Time to access a column. Namemly the number of cycles between the read request and the answer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RAS&lt;/strong&gt; (Row Address Strobe) Precharge Time : Number of cycles between 2 RAS operations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RAS To CAS Dela&lt;/strong&gt;y : Access time to swith from a row to a column.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RAS Active Time&lt;/strong&gt; : Access time for a row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More the timings are low more the chips is fast. But you have to balance the 4 numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's possible to change timings in The BIOS, but these operations can be dangerous for the stability of the chips and also for their life time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This parameter is not the most important to keep in minde, but you cannot ignore it. Timings of 3-3-3-8 or less will be fine. If you have the budget, you can choose 2-2-2-5, but it's very expensive. Keep in mind that timings are lower for DDR3 than for DDR3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--nextpage--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;5. Miscellaneous&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An other question that we can have is "brand chip or noname ? ". This depends on the tastes and the budget, but for the memory i will advice brand chips. The performances are in general really good and the chip is often guaranteed for a long times (sometimes for all the life). In the big constructors of chips we can include Corsair, Kingston or Crucial. You will rarely have problems with chips of these brands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally the memory chips doesn't need to be specially freezed, but on the big configurations very used, it's useful to freeze the chips. The best way is to use a simple heatsink (a lot of chips are directly selled with heatskins. There is also other systems like liquid cooling of fan system. But i've never seen a case where the heatsink isn't enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;6. Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first thing to think about is the necessary quantity of memory. Once this is done, you have to see with your mainboard which chips you can use and make the good choice considering the budget and the need of performances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this article will be useful for the choice of memory chips.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Hardware</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/03/hardware-guide-memory.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2010 13:31:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardware Guide : The Hard Disks</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/02/hardware-guide-hard-disks.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You want buy a new computer, but you cannot which hard disk to buy ? Or you want to buy a new hard disk for your computer ? So, this article is done for you. It will describe all the things you must be careful of when choosing a hard disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hard disk is the element who enables you to store data of your computer. The operating system, your programs, your games and your documents will be stored in this device. So be careful not to stifle your computer choosing an inadequate hard disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you have to control some criterias, like the capacity or the rotation speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/harddisk.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/harddisk-300x174.jpg" alt="Hard Disk" title="Hard Disk" width="300" height="174" class="size-medium wp-image-190"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Capacity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capacity of the hard disk is the quantity of informations it can store. This is the first choice critera, people often search some storage space. But this capacity depends of your needs. The capacity is calculated in Go (Gigaoctets) and the price is directly depending of the capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For informations, 1 Go = 1024 Mo = 1 048 576 Ko = 1 073 741 824 octets. It now common to find hard disks with more than one To (Teraoctets). 1 To = 1024 Go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the necessary capacity, here are the capacity for some applications or files :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A program : Between 10 and 500 Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A video game : Between 200 Mo and several Go&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A Word document of several pages : 50 Ko&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A song in MP3 : 3 to 7 Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A numeric photography : 1 Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A film (DivX format) : 700 Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Windows XP : 5 to 10 Go&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Windows Vista : 10 to 20 Go&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Linux : 5 to 10 Go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is only estimations, but that can allow you to make an idea of what you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not usefull to buy a enormous hard disk when you have only some Word documents to store. The sellers will often try to sell you the biggest hard disks. So keep in mind your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a 1 To hard disk can contains :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;More than 1400 movies in DivX format or&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;1 million of photos in medium format or&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;200'000 songs in MP3 format or&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Several tens of millions of pages in Word format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you can see that this kind of hard disk is often not necessary. I don't say that's a bad idea but it's a good thing to estimate your need before choosing an enormous (or too small). It's not really interesting to use moyen for space that we'll never use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--nextpage--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;3. Physical format&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to decide is the physical format of the hard disk. There is 2 main formats of hard disks, namely :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;3"1/2 : This is the format of hard disks for desktop computer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;2"1/2 : This is the hard disks for laptop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the choice is simple, if you need a hard disk for your laptop, you need a 2"1/2 hard disk otherwise one 3"1/2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is still the problem of external hard disk. In this case, the hard disk is directly inside a container, so this is not a big problem. If you search a little hard disk, opt for a 2"1/2 else in most cases, choose a 3"1/2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. Interface&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing to verify in the interface of the hard disk. That is the way the hard disk will be connected to the motherboard. You cannot connect a SATA hard disk on a motherbord that have only IDE. Here are the main existing formats :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IDE&lt;/strong&gt; (PATA) : This is the oldest interface, but also the most used one. The transfer rate is lowe than the other, but is even so acceptable for a normal usage. In its ATA133 version, the theorical transfer rate is 133 Mo/s&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SATA&lt;/strong&gt; : This interface has better transfer rates than PATA. There is two versions (SATA I and II). They have transfer rates of, respectively 150 Mo/s and 300 Mo/s.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SCSI&lt;/strong&gt; : This interface is still better than SATA, but really the expansive and especially made for servers. Its theoretical transfert can go to 640 Mo/s.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAS&lt;/strong&gt; : Serial Attached SCSI : This is the evolution of SCSI. The transfer rate is better and not distributed between hard disks. But this format is not really widespread and exclusively reserved for servers at this time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also have to keep in mind that hard disk are limited in tranfer rate due to their mechanic state. So the transfer rate of the interface is mostly useful when several hard disks are connected on the same bus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a new PC, it's recommended to opt for SATA hard disks who are the new standard for hard disk. If you really want big transfer rates with many disks or if you want to build a server, you can choose SCSI or SAS depending on your budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--nextpage--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;5. Rotation speed&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard disk is often the slowest element of a PC. It's a lot slower than a processor. It's especially because it's mechanic. A disk is composed of a plate in constant rotation and a read/write head who moves on the plate to read and write the data. So we can improve the data transfer rate improving the rotation speed of the plate. But keep in mind that doesn't really improve the access time because for the transfer time, the principal problem is the shift of the head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have to distinguish here the 2"1/2 and 3"1/2 format because the speeds are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;5.1. Hard disk for laptop : 2"1/2 format&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the different speeds for a 2"1/2 hard disk :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;4200 rpm : It's the old version of the hard disk. That's not a good idea to buy one now.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;5400 rpm : It's the standard speed for laptop hard disk.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;7200 rpm : More and more hard disks are sell with this speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard disk with 5400 rpm is still comfortable, but it's really a good investment to buy a 7200rpm hard disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;5.2. Hard disks for desktop computer : 3"1/2 format&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the different speeds for a 3"1/2 hard disk :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;5400 Tours/min : It's the old version of the hard disk, not used anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;7200 Tours/min : It's the standard speed for desktop hard disk.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;10'000 Tours/min : This is only SATA and SCSI hard disk. The capacity of this kind of disk is often limited.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;15'000 Tours/min : This is only SCSI hard disk. You'll find only this disks in servers, very expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the hard disks for store your data, I recommend to use 7200rpm hard disk. But for the main disk, to store operating system and your programs, i recommend a 10'000 rpm with little capacity (36 or 72 Go). That will improve the start of your system and of your programs. It's really comfortable to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;6. Memory cache&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual hard disk have also a cache memory. This memory is used to store the most used data bits that can be reused. When this data are requested, they come directly from the memory cache so without mechanical access, this is faster. We have several memory cache sizes :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;2Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;8Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;16Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;32Mo&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;64Mo (very rare)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a bad idea to buy disk with less than 8Mo of memory cache. If you can, i recommend you to buy hard disk with at least 16Mo. 32Mo or 64Mo will be better but more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--nextpage--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;7. Internal / External&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call an external hard disk an hard disk who stay outside the computer. This kind of hard disk is inside a container and connected to the computer with a FireWire or USB interface. This is really practical to move data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An other possibility is an eSata interface who start to be available with the last computer and laptop, but not on all the computers. This the external version of the SATA format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you choose an external hard disk in USB, take care to the supported USB version of your computer. Indeed, the USB 1.0 is really slow to make data transfer. If you don't have USB 2.0 in your computer, don't buy an USB hard disk. Otherwise choose an hard disk with USB 2.0 or 3.0 if you have a really recent computer. Normally the USB 3.0 hard disk are compatible with older standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;8. SSD&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;SSD&lt;/strong&gt; (Solid State Drive) is a recent technology but that grows quickly. This is a hard disk but without any mechanic element. The transfer rates are better, the time to start the device is almost null and the device make no noise. Moreover the power consumption is lower and the crashworthiness is also better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the SSD have a limited life duration. Indeed, the memory cells supports only a maximal number of write cycles. This tend to be improved. By example Intel has announced a life duration of 5 years for his SSD X25-M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the price is really more expensive than the price of a tranditional hard disk, 10 to 15 times more if we take the price per Go. En plus de cela, le prix est bien plus élevé que pour un disque dur traditionnel, environ 10 à 15 fois plus en prenant le prix au Go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try SSD, this can really improve the start time of your computer and of your applications. So it's interesting to opt for a little SSD for the operating system (32 or 64 Go). But it's not reasonable to use a SSD to store data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;9. Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, although the capacity is really important, this is not the only criteria. You have to keep in mind the performances of the hard disk (memory cache, rotation speed, interface) to not decrease performances of your computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be also careful of the constructor and the series of the hard disk. It's a good thing to buy a more expensive one of a good construtor instead of a noname hard disk with several problems. Indeed, some series have problems and don't keep their promises at the level of the transfer rate. To know if a hard disk has a good reputation, the best thing is to consult comments of buyers in the sell website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Hardware</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/02/hardware-guide-hard-disks.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2010 13:25:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>