<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>@Blog("Baptiste Wicht") (projects)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/projects.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2016 16:59:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Detect overflows and more in Java with COJAC</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/detect-overflows-and-more-in-java-with-cojac.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back at school, I worked on the COJAC project to detect numeric overflow in
Java programs automatically. Since then, this project has evolved a lot and has
now more features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can detect integer overflows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detect smearing and cancellation with float and double types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detect NaN and Infinite results from computations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detect offending type casting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, all these features are available without any recompilation of your
program. You simply add an argument to the invocation of the Java virtual
machine and all these errors will be detected for you automatically!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frédéric Bapst, the person in charge of the project has recently published two
videos about the project, don't hesitate to check them out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first video presents the automatic analysis features of the tool:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DqAFQfbWZOU?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the second presents the numeric wrapper features of the tool for even more
features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4x9mJEFjcGc?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have any question related to the project, you can add a comment to this
page or contact me directly be email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more information on the project you can also check out its
repository on Github: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Cojac/Cojac"&gt;https://github.com/Cojac/Cojac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>COJAC</category><category>Java</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/detect-overflows-and-more-in-java-with-cojac.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 13:18:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Aggregator Plugin : Display global metrics in Sonarqube</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/aggregator-plugin-display-global-metrics-in-sonarqube.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, I wanted to know how many lines of code I had on my Sonar server with all my C++ projects. Sonarsource proposes a commercial plugins (Views) that allows to do that (and much more...), but I didn't wanted to pay thousands of dollars simply to get a total of my lines of code, therefore I wrote a very  simple Sonar plugin to compute some global metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin is very simple, it only provides a global widgets that aggregates some stats over all your projects. For instance, here is the results on my Sonar server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/aggregator_widget.png" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/aggregator_widget.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plugin is freely available on Github: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/aggregator-plugin"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/aggregator-plugin&lt;/a&gt; . However, it has only be tested on my Sonar server (4.5.2) and it is my first Sonar plugin, so it may not work everywhere. If you experience issues, don't hesitate to open an issue on Github or to propose a Pull Request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can install the plugin by putting the .jar file (from the Github Releases page) into your sonar/extensions/plugins directory and restart Sonar. You should then have access to a new global widget that you can add to a dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this plugin helps some of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>projects</category><category>Releases</category><category>Sonar</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/aggregator-plugin-display-global-metrics-in-sonarqube.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 10:37:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.3.1 - Git versioning and easier creation</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/05/budgetwarrior-031-git-versioning-easier-creation.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've finished a new version of budgetwarrior: budgetwarrior 0.3.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting change is the ability to estimate the date when it is a good time to buy something from the wish list. This is done with the &lt;em&gt;budget wish estimate&lt;/em&gt; command: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="budget wish estimate" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_031_wish_estimate.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This command gives you two dates for each wish in your list. The first is the date wating for each yearly objectives to be fullfilled. The second one considers only the monthly objectives. For now on, no estimation of expenses is made for the future months. It means that the estimation is made as if there were no expenses in the future months. I'll try to improve that by considering averages of expenses in the previous months to make it more reliable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still on the wish module, you can now mark your wishes as paid instead of deleting them. This helps you keep track of the prices of your wishes. This is done with the &lt;em&gt;budget wish paid id&lt;/em&gt; command. Finally, the totals of the unpaid wishes and of the paid wishes is displayed in &lt;em&gt;budget wish list&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another helpful change is the ability to set a date relative to today's date when creating an expense or an earning. For instance, you can create an expense one month before (-1m) or in one year ((+1y) or yesterday (-1d): &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="new date selection mechanism" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_031_date_selection.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can also still set the date manually. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last major change is the addition of a new module: &lt;em&gt;budget versioning&lt;/em&gt;. This module helps you manipulate you budget directory with Git. There are two new commands: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;budget versioning save&lt;/em&gt;: Commit the current changes with a default message (Update). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;budget versioning sync&lt;/em&gt;: Pull the changes from the remote directory and push the local changes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will only works if you have already configured your budget directory to use Git. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll found these changes interesting :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the tool, you can download it on Github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on the github project: &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Git</category><category>Linux</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/05/budgetwarrior-031-git-versioning-easier-creation.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 14:45:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.3.0 - Objective and wish management</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/02/budgetwarrior-0-3-0-objective-wish-management.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to announce the release of another budgetwarrior release, the version 0.3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version contains several important changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is the addition of a new module to manage objectives. You can add objective with &lt;em&gt;budget objective add). &lt;/em&gt;For instance, you can add an objective saying you want to save 10000$ a year or 200$ a month. When you set your objectives, budget warrior computes how well you complete them. For instance, here is the status of my objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113057-e1391337197470.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Objective Status" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113057-e1391337197470-300x83.png" title="Objective Status"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another module has been added to manage wishes. You can add wishes to budgetwarrior (&lt;em&gt;budget wish add&lt;/em&gt;) and then budgetwarrior will tell you if it is a good time to buy them. Here is an example of wish status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113814.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2665" alt="Wish Status" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113814-e1391337576857-300x96.png" width="300" height="96"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Wish Status&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diagnostics tells you where the money will be taken: On savings, on year savings or on month savings (ideal case). It also checks the objectives to see if the payment doesn't break the fulfillment of some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For complete diagnostics, it is necessary to you register your fortune (&lt;em&gt;budget fortune check&lt;/em&gt;), ideally once a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is only a tool, you should not only use that to decide when to buy something, but it may have a good point of view ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the version also have other smaller changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you make an error when creating a new item (expense, earning, ...), the tool now lets you retry without losing what you typed before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confirmation messages are now shown after each modification command (delete, add and edit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The license has been changed from Boost to MIT. The sense is almost the same, but the MIT is more well known and I thought it would be easier for people to know what this means.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There have several changes to the code base, but that doesn't impact the usage of the tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll found these changes interesting :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the tool, you can download it on Github: &lt;a title="budgetwarrior repository" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is now Gentoo and Arch Linux installation packages available for ease of installation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on the github project: &lt;a title="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Linux</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/02/budgetwarrior-0-3-0-objective-wish-management.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 08:21:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.2 - Visual reports, fortune status and expenses aggregates</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/10/budgetwarrior-0-2-visual-reports-fortune-status-expenses-aggregates.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've released a new version of budgetwarrior the version 0.2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've several new features to the tool. First, I've added a graph of the expenses/earnings/balances of each month for a given year in the form of a bar plot. You can see an example in practice here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Screenshot-from-2013-10-25-215839.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2617" alt="budgetwarrior monthly report" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Screenshot-from-2013-10-25-215839-300x266.png" width="300" height="266"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing fancy, but it gives a good overview of the current state of your budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've added a new module, called fortune, that lets you enter your total fortune and then computes the difference between the entered fortune statuses. For now, it doesn't do anything else with this data. But in the future, I want to correlate this data with the balances to check the difference between the filled expenses and earnings and the fortune evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also added a more convenient way of creating expenses and earnings. Just type "budget expense add" and you'll be able to fill all the fields one by one. Of course, the command line commands are still available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last new feature I've added is an aggregate report (budget overview aggregate). This view simply groups all the expenses with the same name of a year together. If you always use the same expense title for your groceries, you'll see the total you spent in groceries for a year. You can also name your expenses with the format "Category/Expenses" and all the expenses with the same category will be grouped together in the aggregate view. That allows you to still have enough details in the monthly overview but to logically groups your expenses together in the aggregate view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other changes are minor. I've improved the monthly overview to sort the expenses and earnings by date. To facilitate the storage of the files in a service like Dropbox, the data and configuration files are now only written if they have been modified. The mean in the current overview has been changed to reflect only the months up to the current month and not the future (which was just ruining the means).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the tool, you can download it on Github: &lt;a title="budgetwarrior repository" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this tool will be useful to some people. If you've any question, just let a comment on this post or contact me directly by email. I'll be glad to help.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Others</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/10/budgetwarrior-0-2-visual-reports-fortune-status-expenses-aggregates.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 14:10:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.1.0 - command-line personal budgeting tool</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/08/budgetwarrior-command-line-personal-budgeting.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being bored by using Google spreadsheets for my personal budgeting, I decided to write an application to do that. Being a huge fan of taskwarrior, I decided to write a kind of similar application for my personal budget, budgetwarrior was born. I use it since two months and I thought that it could be useful for other persons. The application is developed in C++. More information is available on Github: &lt;a title="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;budgetwarrior 0.1.0 is a command-line only tool. It works on this principle: you create a set of accounts with a certain limit and then you declare your expenses in each of these accounts. You can also manage earnings that are not each month in each account. You can also keeps track of your debts via this application. It also supports automatic creation of recurring expenses, for instance when you pay the rent (for now, only monthly expenses are supported).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've put all your data in the application, it provides you report on the state of your budget by month or by year. For instance, here is my current monthly report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145358.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2601" title="Monthly Report" alt="Monthly Report" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145358-300x95.png" width="300" height="95"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see directly which accounts are in a good shape and which are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the current yearly report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145911.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2602" alt="Yearly report" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145911-300x252.png" width="300" height="252"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this view, you can see directly how your accounts evolve during the year and where are your biggest expenses and earnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everything is displayed horizontally, the more accounts you have the larger the view become. With the 7 accounts I have, it takes about 1600 pixels of width to display it. I will try to improve that in the future if some people are interested in making it work on smaller screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can install budgetwarrior directly from the sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;git clone -b master git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
cmake .
make
sudo make install&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, you can use budgetwarrior by using the command &lt;em&gt;budget&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usage is fairly simple, you can use &lt;em&gt;budget help&lt;/em&gt; to have the list of the commands that you have to use to create expenses and earnings and display overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any question on the project, don't hesitate to contact me or to post a comment to this post. If there are people interested, I can write a more complete help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on the github project: &lt;a title="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/08/budgetwarrior-command-line-personal-budgeting.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 06:41:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eddic 1.2.3 - Better data-flow analysis</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/03/eddic-1-2-3-better-data-flow-analysis.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally finished the version 1.2.3 of eddic. I have been quite busy finishing my master thesis in february and then taking some vacations in United States, so this version came later than I wanted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main change is about the speed of the data-flow optimizations. I refactored a lot the data-flow to make it much faster. Some test cases are up to 10 times faster :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still some work to do for speed of optimizations, but it is much better now. Dead Code Elimination and Constant Propagation still have to be made faster, but now the main bottleneck. In the next version of eddic, the parsing performance will be improved. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inlining performance has also been greatly improved. The functions are considered in topological order of the call graph. This makes it much faster and moreover the resulting code is more efficient too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some improvements of the language. char and bool types now takes only one byte each. Copy constructors for structures containing field of structure type are now automatically generated. The grammar has been enhanced to support postfix operations in for loops. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other improvements have been made to the optimization engine. A new optimization has been implemented: Loop Unswitching. This optimization transforms a code like that: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something else&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some code like that: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something else&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;when a doesn't depend on the loop body. The body of the loops is much faster in the second version. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The induction variable analysis is now able to handle loops with induction variable divided in each iteration. With that new feature, the call: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;123&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;is reduced to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sc"&gt;'1'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sc"&gt;'2'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sc"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another small optimization is that variables contributing only to themselves are now correctly identified as dead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the compiler side, the timing system has been greatly improved to contains almost all part of the compilation process. The timings for the complete compilation is available &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic/wiki/Performance" title="Performance"&gt;on the wiki&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Future Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI compiler (eddic) will be the version 1.2.4. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performances will stil be focused for this version. The first change will be to improve the performances of the parsing. Then, I'm gonna try to improve register allocation performances by improving handling of bound registers which I believe is a bottleneck. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also several refactorings that I think of doing to the code. I will probably also implement new minor language features, but I still don't know what. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I have to serve in the army the next three weeks, so there won't be any progress these weeks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI Compiler sources on the Github repository: &lt;a title="Github repository of eddic" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version is available in the &lt;em&gt;v1.2.3&lt;/em&gt; tag available in the GitHub or directly in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Optimization</category><category>projects</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/03/eddic-1-2-3-better-data-flow-analysis.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 10:50:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>