<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (publications)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/publications.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 08:39:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Publications - Sudoku Recognition with Deep Belief Network</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/publications-sudoku-recognition-with-deep-belief-network.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently realized that I never talked about my publications on this website...
I thought it was time to start. I'll start to write a few posts about my earlier
publications and then I'll try to write something for the new ones not too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the story, I'm currently a PHD student at the University of Fribourg, in
Switzerland. My PHD is about the use of Deep Learning technologies to
automatically extract features from images. I have developed my Deep Learning
Library (DLL) project for this thesis. We have published a few articles on the
various projects that we tackled during the thesis. I'll try to go in order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the thesis, I used Restricted Boltzmann Machine and Deep
Belief Network to perform digit recognition on images of Sudoku taken with
a phone camera. We published two papers on this subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/282303748_Camera-based_Sudoku_recognition_with_deep_belief_network"&gt;Camera-based Sudoku Recognition with Deep Belief Network&lt;/a&gt;, in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Soft Computing and Pattern Recognition (SOCPAR-2014)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/307545305_Mixed_handwritten_and_printed_digit_recognition_in_Sudoku_with_Convolutional_Deep_Belief_Network"&gt;Mixed Handwritten and printed digit recognition in Sudoku With Convolutional Deep Belief Network&lt;/a&gt;, in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR-2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sudoku grid and digits are detected using standard image processing
techniques:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The image is first converted to grayscale, then a median blur is applied to
remove noise and the image is binarized using Adapteive Thresholding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The edges are detected using the Canny algorithm. From these, the lines are
detected using a Progressive Probabilistic Hough Transform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a connected component analysis, the segments of lines are clustered
together to detect the Sudoku Grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cells are then detected inside the grid using the inner lines and contour
detection is used to isolate the digits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of the original images from our dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Original image from our dataset" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/image124.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the detected characters from the previous image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Detected digits from our application" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/image124_char.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all the digits have been found they are passed to a Deep Belief Network for
recognition. A Deep Belief Network is composed of several Restricted Boltzmann
Machines (RBM) that are stacked. The network is pretrained, by training each
RBM, in turn, with Contrastive Divergence. This algorithm basically trains each
RBM as an auto-encoder and learns a good feature representation of the inputs.
Once all the layers have been trained, the network can then be trained as
a regular neural network with Stochastic Gradient Descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second paper, the images of Sudoku are containing both computer printed
and handwritten digits (the grid is already filled). The other difference is
that the second system used a Convolutional DBN instead of DBN. The difference
being that each layer is a Convolutional RBM. Such a model will learn a set of
small filters that will be applied to each position of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second version of the dataset, we have been able to achieve 99.14% of
recognition of the digits or 92.5% of fully-recognized grid  with the
Convolutional Network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/sudoku_recognizer"&gt;C++ implementation on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to have a look, I've updated the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/stories/publications.html"&gt;list of my publications&lt;/a&gt;
on this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more details on this project, don't hesitate to ask here or on
Github, or read the paper :)
The next post about my publications will probably be about CPU performances!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>deep learning</category><category>dll</category><category>Personal</category><category>publications</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/publications-sudoku-recognition-with-deep-belief-network.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 07:56:46 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>