<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about Release)</title><link>https://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/release.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 06:46:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>budgetwarrior 1.0.1: Allocation tracking, Retirement calculator and bug fixes</title><link>https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2018/04/budgetwarrior-101-allocation-tracking-retirement-calculator-bug-fixes/</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to announce the release of budgetwarrior 1.0.1. This new version
contains a series of improvement over the 1.0 version and some new features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't been very active this last month. I have been working a bit on
budgetwarrior for features I needed for my budget. I've also been contacted with
questions on my thor operating system and since that point I've doing some
work on thor as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version of budgetwarrior has quite a few new features even though it's
a minor version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The data from all the views is totally randomized and does not make
sense ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="retirement-calculator"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Retirement Calculator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest novelty in this version is the addition of a retirement calculator.
This is still very basic, but it may give information on how close (or far) you
are from early retirement. Here is what the view gives you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Retirement Status" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_101_retirement_status.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using your annual withdrawal rate and expected Rate Of Return, it can compute
how many years you will need to reach your goals Financial Independence (FI). It
will also gives you your FI ratio and a few more information about your savings
rate, income, expenses and so on. It's nothing very fancy but it can be very
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="new-features"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also added a few graphs based on the budget information. The first is the
visualization of the expenses over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Expenses over time graph" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_101_expenses_over_time.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be pretty useful to see how are your expenses going. Even if your
income is going, expenses should not necessarily go up (you should save more!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another new view can show your asset allocation over time and the current asset
allocation of your entire net worth or specifically for your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asset allocation" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_101_allocation.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also really useful if you want to have a global view of your asset
allocation into bonds, stocks and such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also two other new minor features. You can now search expenses by
name. This is really useful once you start having many expenses. Another new
view is the Full aggregate view. Before, you could aggregate your expenses by
month or year, now they can be aggregate since the beginning of the budget. With
this, you can see how much you spend on coffee since you started keeping track
of your budget. For me, it's a lot! Both these features are available both in
command line and in the web interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="improvements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a few improvements with this new version. You can now set
a default account (in the configuration file with default_account=X). It will be
set by default in both the web view and the console view. The rebalance view has
been made more clear. I've added a second batch update view with only the assets
that are being used (amount &amp;gt; 0). And lastly, the yearly overview is now
displaying correctly the previous year savings rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are also a few bug fixes. That is is the main reason I decided to
release now. If you were using asset with different currency, several views
where not correctly using the exchange rate to display them. Moreover, the
average expenses in the monthly overview was not correct. Finally, if you were
editing old expenses after having archived the accounts, it could be edited with
the wrong account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;cite&gt;AUR repository
&amp;lt;https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt; (wait a few days for the new version to be
updated)_&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;git clone --recursive git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
git checkout 1.0.1
make
sudo make install&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to test the server mode, the default username is admin and the
default password is 1234. You can change them in the configuration file with
web_user and web_password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it's a minor version, it improves and fixes quite a few things,
especially for the web view. I encourage you to try it out. Don't hesitate to
let me a comment if you fail to use it or don't understand something ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still a few things that I want to do, as I said when
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2018/01/budgetwarrior-10-web-interface-and-asset-tracking.html"&gt;I introduced the web version&lt;/a&gt;. The website still needs to be
made faster. And the communication between the console and the server can also
be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>projects</category><category>Release</category><guid>https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2018/04/budgetwarrior-101-allocation-tracking-retirement-calculator-bug-fixes/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 08:58:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 1.0: Web interface and asset tracking!</title><link>https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2018/01/budgetwarrior-10-web-interface-and-asset-tracking/</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to announce the release of budgetwarrior 1.0. This is a major change
over the previous version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="web-interface"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Web Interface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, budgetwarrior could only be used in command line. This is fine for
me, but not for every body. Since I wanted to share my budget with my
girlfriend, I needed something less nerdy ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I added support for &lt;em&gt;a web interface for budgetwarrior&lt;/em&gt;. Every feature
of the console application is now available in the web version. Moreover, since
the web version offers &lt;em&gt;slightly better&lt;/em&gt; graphical capabilities, I added a few
more graphs and somewhat more information at some places. I'm not nearly an
expert in web interface, but I think I managed to get something not too bad
together. There are still some things to improve that I'll go through in the
future but so far the web interface is pretty satisfying and it is &lt;strong&gt;mobile friendly&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web server is coded in C++ (who would have guessed...) and is embedded in
the application, you need to use the command &lt;strong&gt;server&lt;/strong&gt; to use it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;budget server&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the server will be launched (by default at localhost:8080). You can
configure the port with &lt;code&gt;server_port=X&lt;/code&gt; in the configuration file and the
listen address with &lt;code&gt;server_listen=X&lt;/code&gt;. You can access your server at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://localhost:8080"&gt;http://localhost:8080&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what this will display:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Web interface index" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_web_index.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: All the data is randomized&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main page shows your assets, the current net worth, your monthly cash-flow
and the state of your objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The menu will give you access to all the features of the application. You can
add expenses and earnings, see reports, manage your assets and your objectives
and so on. Basically, you can do everything you did in the application, but you
have access to more visualization tools than you would on the console. For
instance, you can access your fortune over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Web interface fortune graph" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_web_fortune.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or see how your portfolio does in terms of currency:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Web interface portofolio currency breakdown" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_web_portfolio_currency.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, unless I forgot something (in which case, I'll fix it), everything
should be doable from the web interface. This is simply easier people that are
not as nerdy as me for console ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The management is still the same, the server will write to the same file the
base application uses. Therefore, you cannot use the server and the command line
application on the same machine at the same time. Nevertheless, if the server is
not running, you can still use the command line application. This could be
useful if you want to use the web visualization while still using the command
line tool for managing the budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default user and password is admin:1234, but you of course change it using
web_password and web_user in the configuration. You can also disable the
security if you are sure of yourself by setting &lt;code&gt;server_secure=true&lt;/code&gt; in
the configuration. The server currently does not support&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, it does not protect against concurrent modifications of the same
data. It is very unlikely to happen with only a few people using the
applications, but I plan to improve that in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="server-mode"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Server mode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it's not possible to use both the server and the command line
application at the same time, it's possible to use the command line application
in server mode. In this case, instead of reading and writing the data from the
hard disk, the application will send requests to the server to read and write
the data it needs. With this, you can use both the server and the command line
application at the same time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While running, the server exposes a simple API that can be used to get
all the information about the budget data and that can also be used to add new
expenses, earnings and so on directly to the server data. The API is also
protected by authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the server does not support HTTPS. However, you can run it behind
a proxy such as nginx which is running in HTTPS. This is what I'm doing. The
server mode supports SSL from the client to the server, you just have to set
&lt;code&gt;server_sll=true&lt;/code&gt; in the configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the mode I'm currently using and will continue using. With this, I can
quickly do some modifications using the command line and if I want to see
advanced visualization, I just have to open my browser and everything is
updated. Moreover, in the future, other people involved with my budget will be
able to access the web interface. This also solves the synchronization problem
in a much better way than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as it was the case with the server, this is not made to be used in parallel
by different users. This should be perfectly fine for a small household.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="assets-tracking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assets Tracking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already a few months ago, I've added &lt;cite&gt;the feature to track assets &amp;lt;https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/budgetwarrior-track-assets-portfolio-savings-rates-auto-completion.html&amp;gt; `_ into budgetwarrior. You can define the list of the assets you possess. The tool will then help you track the value of your assets. You can set your desired distribution of bonds, cash and stocks and the tool will help you see if you need to rebalance your assets. This will let you compute your net worth, with :code:`budget asset value&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="View of your assets" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_asset_values.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, you can also set a few of your assets as your portfolio assets. These
assets have a desired distribution and are handled different. These are the
assets you directly manage yourself, your investment portfolio. You can then
track their value and see if they need rebalancing. For instance, here is
a randomized rebalancing of your portfolio, with &lt;code&gt;budget asset rebalance&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="View of the needed rebalance" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_rebalance.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these features are now also available on the web version as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="better-console-usability"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Better console usability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I added some &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/budgetwarrior-track-assets-portfolio-savings-rates-auto-completion.html"&gt;quality-of-life improvements to the console appplication&lt;/a&gt;. You can now cycle through the list of possible values for accounts for instance in the console! This is down with the UP and DOWN keys. Now, I also added auto-completion with TAB key. You can write Ins&amp;lt;TAB&amp;gt; and it will complete to Insurances if you have an Insurances account in your budget. This makes it much faster to enter new expenses or to update asset values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Installation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;cite&gt;AUR repository
&amp;lt;https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt; (wait a few day for the new version to be
updated)_&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;git clone --recursive git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
git checkout 1.0
make
sudo make install&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, even though I'm not a fan of web development, it was quite fun to add
all these features to budgetwarrior and made it much better I think. This is
a very significant change to the project since it almost doubled in number of
source lines of code, but I think it's a change that was needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think these changes really make budgetwarrior more useful to a wider group of
people and I'm pretty to have finally come around and implemented them. I still
have a few things I plan to improve in the near future. First, I want to make
the website a bit faster, there are many scripts and stylesheets that are being
loaded and make the site a bit bloated. I'll also enable gzip compression of the
website to speed up things. I will also ensure that the server can handle
requests concurrently without any problem of the data (should be simple since we
don't need high performance). I may also add a new module to budgetwarrior to
track your progress towards retirement if this is something you are interested
in, but I haven't decided in what form exactly. Finally, I will also try to
optimize the requests that are being done between the server and the client when
run in server mode. Indeed, it currently downloads almost all the data from the
server which is far from optimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>projects</category><category>Release</category><guid>https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2018/01/budgetwarrior-10-web-interface-and-asset-tracking/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 11:52:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Expression Templates Library (ETL) 1.2 - Complete GPU support</title><link>https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/expression-templates-library-etl-1-2-complete-gpu-support/</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;img alt="ETL Logo" class="align-center" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/logo.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to announce the version 1.2 of my Expression Templates Library (ETL):
ETL 1.2, two months after &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/08/expression-templates-library-etl-11.html"&gt;I released the version 1.1&lt;/a&gt;.
This version features much better GPU Support, a few new features and a lot of
changes in the internal code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="gpu-support"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GPU Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before, only algorithms such as 4D convolution or matrix-matrix multiplication
were computed in the GPU and lots of operations were causing copies between CPU
and GPU version. Now, the support for basic operations has also been completed
and therefore, expressions like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code cpp"&gt;&lt;a id="rest_code_261c06c0a9d14e7aa5a8c81e7736365c-1" name="rest_code_261c06c0a9d14e7aa5a8c81e7736365c-1" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/expression-templates-library-etl-1-2-complete-gpu-support/#rest_code_261c06c0a9d14e7aa5a8c81e7736365c-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sigmoid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;2.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can be computed entirely on GPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each matrix and vector containers have a secondary GPU memory space.  During the
execution, the status of both memory spaces is being managed and when necessary,
copies are made between two spaces. In the best case, there should only be
initial copies to the GPU and then everything should be done on the GPU. I've
also considered using Unified Memory in place of this system, but this is
a problem for fast matrix and I'd rather not have two different systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have an expression such as &lt;code&gt;c = a + b * 2&lt;/code&gt;, it can be entirely computed
on GPU, however, it will be computed in two GPU operations such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code cpp"&gt;&lt;a id="rest_code_85d45ed7928f4d81a8db7e4e2bc6fa0d-1" name="rest_code_85d45ed7928f4d81a8db7e4e2bc6fa0d-1" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/expression-templates-library-etl-1-2-complete-gpu-support/#rest_code_85d45ed7928f4d81a8db7e4e2bc6fa0d-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;t1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a id="rest_code_85d45ed7928f4d81a8db7e4e2bc6fa0d-2" name="rest_code_85d45ed7928f4d81a8db7e4e2bc6fa0d-2" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/expression-templates-library-etl-1-2-complete-gpu-support/#rest_code_85d45ed7928f4d81a8db7e4e2bc6fa0d-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;t1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not perfect in terms of performance but this will be done without any
copies between CPU and GPU memory. I plan to improve this system with a bit more
complex operations to avoid too many GPU operations, but there will always be
more operations than in CPU where this can easily be done in one go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few expressions that are not computable on the GPU, such as random
generations. A few transformations are also not fully compatible with GPU.
Moreover, if you access an element with operators &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;()&lt;/code&gt;, this
will invalidate the GPU memory and force an update to the CPU memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPU operations are not implemented directly in ETL, there are coming from
various libraries. ETL is using NVIDIA CUDNN, CUFFT and CUDNN for most
algorithms. Moreover, for other operations, I've implemented a libraries with
simple GPU operations: ETL-GPU-BLAS (EGBLAS). You can have a look at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/etl-gpu-blas"&gt;egblas&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Deep Learning Library (DLL) project is based on ETL and its performances are
mostly dependent on ETL's performances. Now that ETL fully supports GPU, the
GPU performance of DLL is much improved. You may remember a few weeks ago
I posted &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/08/dll-blazing-fast-neural-network-library.html"&gt;very high CPU performance of DLL&lt;/a&gt;.
Now, I've run again the tests to see the GPU performance with DLL. Here is the
performance for training a small CNN on the MNIST data set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Performances for training a Convolutional Neural Network on MNIST" class="align-center" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/etl_12_dll_gpu_mnist.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the performances on GPU are now excellent. DLL's performances
are on par with Tensorflow and Keras!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next results are for training a much larger CNN on ImageNet, with the time
necessary to train a single batch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Performances for training a Convolutional Neural Network on Imagenet" class="align-center" src="https://baptiste-wicht.com/images/etl_12_dll_gpu_imagenet.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, using the new version of ETL inside DLL has led to excellent performance.
The framework is again on par with TensorFlow and Keras and faster than all the
other frameworks. The large difference between DLL and Tensorflow and Keras is
due to the inefficiency of reading the dataset in the two frameworks, so the
performance of the three framework themselves are about the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="other-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other Changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The library also has a few other new features. Logarithms of base 2 and base 10
are now supported in complement to the base e that was already available before.
Categorical Cross Entropy (CCE) computation is also available now, the CCE loss
and error can be computed for one or many samples. Convolutions have also been
improved in that you can use mixed types in both the image and the kernel and
different storage order as well. Nevertheless, the most optimized version
remains the version with the same storage order and the same data type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also made a major change in the way implementations are selected for each
operation. The tests and the benchmark are using a system to force the selection
of an algorithm. This system is now disabled by default. This makes the
compilation much faster by default. Since it's not necessary in most cases, this
will help regular use cases of the library by compiling much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the support for complex numbers has been improved in ETL. There are
more routines that are supported and &lt;code&gt;etl::complex&lt;/code&gt; is better supported
throughout the code. I'll still work on this in the future to make it totally
complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internal code also has a few new changes. First, all traits have been
rewritten to use variable templates instead of struct traits. This makes the
code much nicer in my opinion. Moreover, I've started experimenting with C++17
&lt;code&gt;if constexpr&lt;/code&gt;. Most of the if conditions that can be transformed to if
constexpr have been annotated with comments that I can quickly enable or disable
so that I can test the impact of C++17, especially on compilation time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a few bugs have been fixed. ETL is now working better with parallel
BLAS library. There should not be issues with double parallelization in ETL and
BLAS. There was a slight bug in the Column-Major matrix-matrix multiplication
kernel. Binary operations with different types in the left and right hand sides
was also problematic with vectorization. The last bug was about GPU status in
case ETL containers were moved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="what-s-next"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's next ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't yet know exactly on which features I'm going to focus for the next
version of ETL. I plan to focus a bit more in the near future on Deep Learning
Library (DLL) for which I should release the version 1.0 soon. I also plan to
start support for Recurrent Neural Networks on it, so that will take me quite
some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I'm still planning to consider the switch to C++17, since it is
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/09/how-i-made-deep-learning-library-38-faster-to-compile-optimization-and-cpp17-if-constexpr.html"&gt;a bit faster to compile ETL with if constexpr&lt;/a&gt;. The next version of ETL will also probably have GPU-support for
integers, at least in the cases that depend on the etl-gpu-blas library, which
is the standard operators. I also plan to improve the support for complex
numbers, especially in terms of performance and tests. Hopefully, I will have also time (and motivation)
to start working on  the sparse capabilities of ETL. It really needs much more
unit tests and the performance should be improved as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="download-etl"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Download ETL&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download ETL &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/etl"&gt;on Github&lt;/a&gt;. If you
only interested in the 1.2 version, you can look at the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/etl/releases"&gt;Releases pages&lt;/a&gt; or clone the tag
1.2. There are several branches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; Is the eternal development branch, may not always be stable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;stable&lt;/em&gt; Is a branch always pointing to the last tag, no development here&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the future release, there always will tags pointing to the corresponding
commits. You can also have access to previous releases on Github or via the
release tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation is still a bit sparse. There are a few examples and the Wiki,
but there still is work to be done. If you have questions on how to use or
configure the library, please don't hesitate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to comment this post if you have any comment on this library or
any question. You can also open an Issue on Github if you have a problem using
this library or propose a Pull Request if you have any contribution you'd like
to make to the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope this may be useful to some of you :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>C++14</category><category>C++17</category><category>Compilers</category><category>dll</category><category>etl</category><category>GPU</category><category>Performance</category><category>projects</category><category>Release</category><guid>https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/expression-templates-library-etl-1-2-complete-gpu-support/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 08:49:02 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>