<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>@Blog("Baptiste Wicht") (Review)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/review.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 14:58:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola &lt;http://getnikola.com/&gt;</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ri-Vier RV 2004 Rackmount case Review</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/05/ri-vier-rv-2004-rackmount-case-review.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ordered a new rackmount case for my third server at home. Previously, I only used Norco cases, but the European distributor of Norco (Ri-vier, Netherlands) decided to switch to using its own cases, the Ri-vier cases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the shipping fees are very expensive from United States to Switzerland, I decided to stick with Ri-vier for now and try their new cases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered and received the RV-2004 case. This is a 2U case with one 5.25" and 4 3.5". It is a very short case. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of the case: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="RV-2004 case" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/RVS-2004_1_LRG.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks quite good actually and very like the Norco equivalents. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is the front: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="RV-2004 case front view" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/RVS-2004_4_LRG.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can put a DVD reader on front. There are also two USB ports and several leds. I really don't like the front panel. There a lot of screws that maintain the front panel. Moreover, the part with the buttons and the LEDs is quite hard to put right and seems of really low facture, I haven't been able to make the LEDs work as of now. The buttons have a kind of plastic cap on them, but it is very hard to make them stay on the buttons when you install the front panel. Finally, there are two fans on the front on their own panel. You can remove the fans, but they are so close together, that most silent fans you will buy won't fit side by side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And an inner view: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="RV-2004 case inner view" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/RVS-2004_7_LRG.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three hard disk top cases are removable. In my case, I only left one of them for the SSD. The rightmost one is very hard to pull in and out. I don't understand why there are only three removable cases. The fourth disk location cannot be moved. As with all other cases, it it not very practical to install a SSD in it. I ended up screwing the SSD on top of one of the removable bays. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without any media drive and only one SSD, there are plenty of space inside the case to put the cables. Even with all the bays used, there would probably be some space left under the drive bays. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mouting the motherboard inside the case was really easy, nothing special here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case is only mountable with RVR-20 rails, not with the Norco RL rails. These rails are really worse than the Norco rails. There are extensible, being in three parts, but the extension is not as good as Norco's. If you extend the rails, you have to mount the rails close to the rear of the case. Moreover, the clip on rails to unblock them does not seem to work on my rails. Fortunately, that is not a case I intend to upgrade in the future, so I should not use the rails extensively. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Super short&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enough room on the inside&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Looks quite nice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fans too close to each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Front panel very cheaply built&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Front panel hard to put correctly in place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the removable hard drive internal bays is very hard to move&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very poor rails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish, I would say that I'm kind of disappointed with this case. It really feels worse than the Norco equivalent. I'd rather have Norco cases again. The only advantage it has over the Norco one is being cheaper. I'm probably gonna go for a Norco case again for my next server. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Server</category><category>Review</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/05/ri-vier-rv-2004-rackmount-case-review.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 11:40:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Norco RPC 230 Case Review</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/08/norco-rpc-230-case-review.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As my previous Dell 1U server was &lt;a title="Home Server Adventure – Step 1" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1/"&gt;too noisy for my home server installation&lt;/a&gt;. I invested in a case, a Norco RPC 230 model. This case is a 2U standard case for 19" rack. It supports micro-ATX motherboard and ATX power supply. These components are easy too find, so that makes it a very interesting case for a home server installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the case at &lt;a title="Ri-Vier Automatisering" href="https://ri-vier.eu/"&gt;Ri-Vier Automatisering&lt;/a&gt;, which is the Norco european distributor. I directly ordered it with the RL-26 rails for the rack and the ATX power supply that is provided by Ri-Vier. For the case, I also bought a micro-ATX Gigabyte G41M-Combo motherboard. I already had 4GB of DDR2 RAM and a Core 2 Duo processor from a previous configuration. I also took my old 120GB Samung SSD for this server. This would be largely sufficient for what I plan to run on this server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case has four 3.5" drive bays and one 5.25" drive bay. The air flow is provided with two 80mm fans on the front panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Package&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received the package very quickly from Ri-Vier. The case is packaged in double box and everything in the package is well ordered. The power supply was already in the box itself. Here is a picture of the content of the package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.45.14.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2596" alt="2013-08-20 09.45.14" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.45.14-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It contains only the case and the necessary screws. The rails are not on this picture, since I already had installed them in my rack. As you see, there are no manual, which may be a bit frustrating. Once you remove the top panel (4 screws to remove), you can see the inside of the case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.54.09.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2595" alt="2013-08-20 09.54.09" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-09.54.09-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the top are the four bays for the drives. They are removable. As you can see on the picture, the power supply has plenty of cables. I would have expected a power supply with less cables to come with this case as there is not much room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a view of the front panel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.22.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2593" alt="2013-08-20 11.11.22" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.22-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two USB ports on the front, the Power and Reset buttons as well as LEDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even without any manual, the installation is fairly easy. The top panel can be removed by unscrewing 4 four screws on the side. I strongly recommend to remove the 4 drive bays before installing the other components to make some room. Once it is done, the motherboard can be screwed in place. The power supply is attached by four screws on the back panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed a SSD 2.5" in the leftmost disk bay. I had some issues with this installation as the bays do not have any screws on the side, only on the bottom. They are really not made for anything else than 3.5" drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of my installation once finished:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.39.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2592" alt="2013-08-20 11.11.39" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.11.39-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to make it looks nice with the cables, but only because I have not installed any CD-Rom, so I did put a lot of cables in its place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it is done, I have installed it in my rack. It is not straightforward without a manual, but I was able to screw it to the rails. I did put two screws on each side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.08.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2591" alt="2013-08-20 11.31.08" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.08-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in place, it looks quite good:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.51.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2590" alt="2013-08-20 11.31.51" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-20-11.31.51-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I don't know if I have done something wrong, but the rails are not sliding smoothly, they are blocking at two places and the last part is quite hard to push. Anyway, as I won't be moving it a lot, I think it is ok. You also have to remember that even if it is a short depth case, the RL-26 rails are not short at all, they are not made for short depth racks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it is launched, the server is quite busy due to the two 80mm fans. However, the airflow is quite strong, which is what most customers want. It is still more silent than my Dell server, but not enough for a home experience. I will try to replace them with more silent fans in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pros&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;Enough bays for a simple server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support standard formats&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Enough air flow&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Very short depth&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Seems of heavy duty construction&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Looks nice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Not too expensive&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Should fit in most racks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;No manuals at all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Disk bays not very convenient&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The provided power supply is not very adapted to the case.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The provided rails seems to not slide smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, I would say that this case is very fit to a custom installation as all the components are standards. I would recommend it for a similar usage than mine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Server</category><category>Review</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/08/norco-rpc-230-case-review.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 06:38:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ZyXEL GS1910-24 Managed Gigabit Switch Review</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/07/zyxel-gs1910-managed-gigabit-switch-review.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A short time ago, &lt;a title="Home Server Adventure – Step 1" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2013/07/home-server-adventure-step-1/"&gt;I decided to install servers in a rack at my home&lt;/a&gt;. Although working very well, my 3Com managed was too much noisy for being at home. That is why I decided to change it for fanless switch. After some research, I finally chose a ZyXEL GS1910-24. It is a web-manageable gigabit switch. I chose the 24 ports version. This version has also 4 SFPs that replace 4 normal ports if enabled. I don't think I will ever need the SFPs, but it is nice to know that there are here if necessary. This switch has a lot of cool features, it supports IPV6, QoS, VLANs, filtering, RADIUS and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The package&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package does not contains a lot of things, but does contain the essential:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 13px;"&gt;The switch itself&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A power code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rack mounting brackets and screws&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Manuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture on the package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-16.51.47.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2574" alt="2013-07-11 16.51.47" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-16.51.47-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch is really small, twice narrower than my 3Com switch and more than twice lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing special to say about the package, it is neatly done and has everything that is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation inside a rack is really easy. Each bracket is mounted with 4 screws onto the switch and then two screws are holding each bracket into place in the rack. Here is a picture of the rack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-17.07.00.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2575" alt="2013-07-11 17.07.00" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/2013-07-11-17.07.00-300x168.jpg" width="300" height="168"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you put the power cord, it directly starts up and everything already works fine. The state of each port is represented by a led. Orange indicates a 100Mbit/s connection while green indicates 1Gbit/s connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch does not make a single noise and does not vibrate, it is really good&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to configure the switch is to use the web configurator. By default, the switch IP is 192.168.1.1. As my router had the same IP, I had to disable it temporarily before changing the IP of the switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web configuration is very complete, you can change absolutely everything from here. You have also access to a lot of monitoring tools from here. The most useful being of course the port monitoring interface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Screenshot-from-2013-07-11-172745.png"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2576" alt="Port Monitoring" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Screenshot-from-2013-07-11-172745-300x132.png" width="300" height="132"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend changing the default IP address and the server password as first things on the switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't make the list of everything that is configurable on this switch, but the list is pretty impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm really impressed by this switch. The switch is highly configurable and seems to perfectly fit my need. I would totally recommend this switch for rack installation at home. You can also totally use it as a desktop switch if you needs for a big switch on your desktop too&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Hardware</category><category>Home Server</category><category>Network</category><category>Server</category><category>Review</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/07/zyxel-gs1910-managed-gigabit-switch-review.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 06:38:17 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>