<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>@Blog("Baptiste Wicht") (SEO)</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://wichtounet.github.io/categories/seo.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 20:41:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola &lt;http://getnikola.com/&gt;</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>New Wordpress theme for the site</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2011/11/new-theme-site.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a long time with the old F2 theme, I decided to choose a more modern design. I chose the WP Plus design which is based on the Google Plus Design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that this design is more practical and cleaner for the users and more comfortable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I also took some time to change some of my addons. I replaced All In One SEO with Wordpress SEO plugin from Joost de Valk. I think that this plugin is better than the first one, but more of that, it also replaced one addon generating the XML sitemap and helped me adding a breadcrumb to the site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that these changes will improve the user experience on my website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you encounter any kind of problems with the new design, don't hesitate to let a comment or to contact me. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Personal</category><category>SEO</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2011/11/new-theme-site.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 01:56:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Top 15 Best Wordpress Plugins</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/07/top-15-best-wordpress-plugins.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When working on a Wordpress site or blog, it's essential to install several plugins to optimize the site readibility, accessibility, performances, ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are 15 plugins that I think the best of the Wordpress plugins and that I use everyday. The list is not in interest order but in alphabetical order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Akismet" href="http://akismet.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Akismet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Avoid spam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin automatically filters spams for you. It's really simple, you just have to install it and it works great. In my little blog, it filters more than hundred spams a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Akismet.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-798" title="Akismet Stats" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Akismet-300x270.png" alt="Akismet Stats" width="300" height="270"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="All in One SEO Pack" href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/all-in-one-seo-pack/" target="_blank"&gt;All in One SEO Pack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Improve your SEO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin helps you to improve the SEO capability of your website. It can automatically generate the keywords and description of the posts and it give you forms to set the meta informations of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Dagon Design Sitemap Generator" href="http://www.dagondesign.com/articles/sitemap-generator-plugin-for-wordpress/" target="_blank"&gt;Dagon Design Sitemap Generator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Simple sitemap generator&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin generate a simple sitemap for your website content. You can see an example &lt;a title="My sitemap" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/plan/" target="_blank"&gt;on my website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Google Analytics for Wordpress" href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/google-analytics-for-wordpress/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Analytics for Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Get stats of your visitors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin integrates Google Analytics in your website. But this plugin makes a lot more, it also add custom variables to your stats to track your tags and categories in Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Google XML Sitemap Generator" href="http://www.arnebrachhold.de/projects/wordpress-plugins/google-xml-sitemaps-generator/" target="_blank"&gt;Google XML Sitemap Generator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Generate a XML Sitemap for Google&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin generate a XML Sitemap for search engines and keep it up to date with your site content. For referencing your website it's really important to have a XML sitemap and to update it regularly. With this plugin, you have nothing to do. Just write your posts and they will be included in the sitemap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Most Commented Widget" href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/most-commented/" target="_blank"&gt;Most Commented Widget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Add a widget with the most commented posts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, WordPress don't provide a widget to display the most commented posts of the blog. But I think, it's really an interesting things for the readers. So this reader adds this widget and allows you to choose the number of posts to display and the number of days in which we take the posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/MostCommented.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-full wp-image-799" title="Most Commented Posts Widget" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/MostCommented.png" alt="Most Commented Posts Widget" width="216" height="178"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Random Posts Widget" href="http://www.romantika.name/v2/wordpress-plugin-random-posts-widget/" target="_blank"&gt;Random Posts widget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Add a widget with some random posts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An other interesting widget is this one that display some random posts. It's a good idea to improve the visibility of some posts. In this widget you can choose how many posts you want to be displayed and from which category we must take them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/RandomPosts.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-full wp-image-800" title="Random Posts Widget" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/RandomPosts.png" alt="Random Posts Widget" width="217" height="187"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Optimize DB" href="http://yoast.com/wordpress/optimize-db/" target="_blank"&gt;Optimize DB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Avoid overhead on your tables&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin is one of the little you'll find but one of the most useful. It allows you to optimize your database from your admin panel to avoid overhead in WordPress tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/OptimizeDB.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-801" title="Optimize-DB Plugin" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/OptimizeDB-300x99.png" alt="Optimize-DB Plugin" width="300" height="99"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Secure WordPress" href="http://www.sitesecuritymonitor.com/secure-wordpress-plugin" target="_blank"&gt;Secure WordPress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Improve security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin is not useful for your users but to prevent simple attacks to your blog. This plugin executes several tasks to secure your WordPress installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Subscribe to comments" href="http://txfx.net/wordpress-plugins/subscribe-to-comments/" target="_blank"&gt;Subscribe To Comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Let the users subscribe to comments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a user post a comment in your website, he want perhaps be notified about the next comments on the same post. This plugin adds exactly this feature to your blog. The users can subscribe to the comments on one post to be notified by email of the next comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Twitter Widget Pro" href="http://xavisys.com/wordpress-plugins/wordpress-twitter-widget/" target="_blank"&gt;Twitter Widget Pro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Add a widget with your tweets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin add a widget to display your last tweets and a link to follow you on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/TwitterWidgetPro.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-full wp-image-802" title="Twitter Widget Pro" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/TwitterWidgetPro.png" alt="Twitter Widget Pro" width="229" height="532"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="W3 Total Cache" href="http://www.w3-edge.com/wordpress-plugins/w3-total-cache/" target="_blank"&gt;W3 Total Cache&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Improve your performances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want good performances on your WordPress blog, W3 Total Cache is the best plugin you can ever found. For more informations, don't hesitate to read this article I wrote about it : &lt;a title="Improve performances of WordPress using W3 Total Cache" href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2010/05/improve-performances-wordpress-w3-total-cache/"&gt;Improve performances of WordPress with W3 Total Cache&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="Wordpress Related Posts" href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wordpress-23-related-posts-plugin/" target="_blank"&gt;WordPress Related Posts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Generate related posts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin generate a list of related post to each of your post. This is a great way to give to your users a list of post related to their current reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/RelatedPosts.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-full wp-image-803" title="Related Posts" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/RelatedPosts.png" alt="Related Posts" width="523" height="157"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="WP-Syntax" href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wp-syntax/" target="_blank"&gt;WP-Syntax&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Syntax higlighting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an essential plugin for all persons who post code in their blog. It provide syntax higlighting for a lot of languages (more than 70). I principally use Java, HTML and XML. The renderering is quite simple but works well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/WPSyntax.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-804" title="WP Syntax Highlighting" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/WPSyntax-300x112.png" alt="WP Syntax Highlighting" width="300" height="112"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a title="WPtouch iPhone Theme" href="http://www.bravenewcode.com/products/wptouch-pro/"&gt;WPtouch iPhone Theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Make your site accessible on Iphone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This little plugin create an iPhone theme for your website. It's generated automatically, you have nothing to do, so when a visitor visit your blog from iPhone, it automatically see a theme adapted to this phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/WPTouch.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="size-full wp-image-805" title="WP Touch iPhone Theme" src="http://wichtounet.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/WPTouch.jpg" alt="WP Touch iPhone Theme" width="386" height="742"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these plugins are available in the WordPress repository so you can automatically install them from your blog without any problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>SEO</category><category>Web</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/07/top-15-best-wordpress-plugins.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2010 07:02:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>10 most useful Google Tools</title><link>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/04/10-most-useful-google-tools.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than provide an extremely powerful search engine used by almost everybody, &lt;strong&gt;Google&lt;/strong&gt; provides also a lot of very useful tools. In this post, i list the 10 most useful Google tools from my point of view.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;1. Gmail&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this is the best email client ever. The interface is quick and reactive and there are many interesting features. The spam filter is really powerful, i have no more spams since i've switched to GMail a long time ago. The storage capacity (~7.4 Go) is also totally enough. Moreover, this client is totally integrated with the other tools of the Google network (Documents, Buzz, Agenda, ...). With the plugins, you can also add several others features to GMail including integrating with other tools like RememberTheMilk by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The included chat is also a great functionality. I use it everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No more spam with : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/mail/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Mail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;2. Google Chrome&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly the most efficient browser. The performances of this browser are simply amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are perhaps less plugins now that in Firefox, but it's a lot more lighter than the others browsers.  The tab system is really well done. If a site crashes, you can simply close the tabs ands that's fine. You can also move a tab to an other window with drag&amp;amp;drop facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last months, the number of modules tend to grow quickly and provides the more useful plugins that we could have used in other browsers before switching to Chrome. And Google Chrome support without plugins the synchronization of bookmarks and execution of GreaseMonkey scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And last but not least, this is the most simplistic (not pejorative at all) browser i use and really easy and comfortable to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it and why not like it : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/chrome/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Google Analytics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Analytics is a really great web analytics solution. This is the most used solution. This tool is free for website with less than 5 million page views by month or for those who have an AdWords account. The interface is really simple to use but powerful. All the stats are displayed with number metrics and graphs. And, really important, the traffic analyzer is powerful and light. You can even use an asynchronous JavaScript code to produce less overhead on the page load time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create scheduled reports and email it at a specific time rate. You can also analyze only a fragment of the traffic and follow accomplishments of objectives. You can also use Google Analytics from other languages like PHP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, as a webmaster, this tool is completely essential and I cannot live without it (exaggerate, but I use it everyday).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you try it, you will not regret : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. Google Reader&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Reader is a web aggregator to read RSS and Atom. This web application can work in offline mode accessing all the previously downloaded articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More to be an aggregator, Google Reader has also social network features. In fact, you can share you favorite articles and comment them. You can access to the shared articles of your friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create folders to sort your subscriptions by theme (or any kind of sort you  like) and quickly find what's new in any folder. Google Reader can also give you a list of subscriptions take can interest you based on your current subscriptions themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aggregate your RSS and Atom : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/reader/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;5. Google Webmaster Tools&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Webmaster Tools is an essential tools for all webmaster. With it, you can manage all your websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, you can verify how your site is referenced on Google Search Engine. You can see in which position you are for the most important query for your website. You can see which keywords are the significant for your pages, you can obtain the number of links pointing to your website and to which pages there is the more links. You can also notify Google for updates in your sitemaps. Your internal links are also displayed. You can even consult the Google Reader subcribers to your feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you have also diagnostics about your site. The available diagnostics are the malware detected by the Google robots, crawl errors and crawl stats. Google Webmaster Tools give you some suggestions about your HTML pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will love : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Webmaster Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;6. Google Documents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Documents is an online documents sharing application. In that application, you can create and share documents, presentation, spreadsheets, forms and drawings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than creating and editing the documents, you  can sharing them to anybody that have a Google Acount. The documents are saved by revisions and you can come back to an older revision or merge some revisions. This a really powerful feature when several persons work on the same documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the type of documents can be edited in Wysiwyg way with powerful editors. You can also upload any files you want to your Google Documents account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try : &lt;a href="http://docs.google.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;7. Google Agenda&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Agenda is a simple tools to keep appointments in mind. You have recall for your events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create events and share them to any other Google contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/calendar" target="_blank"&gt;Google Agenda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;8. Google Friend Connect&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Friend Connect is web tools to add social networking features to a website. You can create a community around your website. The visitors can register to your site with simple widgets and no registration using their Google, Facebook or OpenID accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add a lot of widgets to your website, by example to give the users the possibility to rate your contact, ask questions to your visitors or send newsletters to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give it a try : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/friendconnect/" target="_blank"&gt;Google Friend Connect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;9. Keyword Tool&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keyword Tool is an application uuseful to get ideas of keywords for your website or to compare some keywords by Advertiser Competition and Search Volume. That can really help you to choose the keywords you will to focus on to improve the referencing of a website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can directly give a page of your website to the program. The page will be inspected for keywords and the tool will give you a list of keywords ideas based on the content of the site. Or you can give a list of keywords you're interested in and the program will compute a list of other keywords based on yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's an essential tool for all webmaster that like to improve its websites referencing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it : &lt;a href="https://adwords.google.com/select/KeywordToolExternal" target="_blank"&gt;Google Adwords : Keyword Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;10. Google Language Tools&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Language Tools is a simple set of tools to translate text from a language to another. You have several choices : translate some search results, translate a complete web page or translate a given text. There is a lot of available languages. The page give also an access too Google Homepage in all languages. You can note that this tool is integrated with Google Chrome in which you can translate (automatically or manually) pages to your languages with actions in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this very simple, but that works well and that's really useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it : &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/language_tools" target="_blank"&gt;Google Language Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is a lot of others powerful Google Tools. Here are only the  most useful from my point of view. Perhaps a photograph will like Picasa, an advertiser will like AdWords and AdSense and Android, Google Maps Navigation and Google SkyMap for a mobile user.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Google</category><category>SEO</category><category>Tools</category><category>Web</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://wichtounet.github.io/posts/2010/04/10-most-useful-google-tools.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2010 06:24:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>