<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>@Blog("Baptiste Wicht") (Sonar)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2014 22:46:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Sonar 2.1 has been released</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/05/sonar-2-1-has-been-released.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The version 2.1 of Sonar has just been released. This version includes 51 bugfixes and improvements. The major new features are :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A new page "Librairies" displays all the librairies of the project (Maven dependencies)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A new page "Dependencies" searches for library usages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A new page "System Info" display the system properties, installed plugins, database and VM memory stats.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;New rules to detect unused methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, all the plugins compatible with version 2.0 should be compatible with this new version.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Java</category><category>Releases</category><category>Sonar</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/05/sonar-2-1-has-been-released.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 08:45:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First build of JTheque with Sonar 2.0</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/05/first-build-jtheque-sonar-2-0.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This week-end I updated the version of Sonar to &lt;a href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2010/03/sonar-2-0-released/"&gt;the new version 2.0&lt;/a&gt; and migrated it from Tomcat 5.5 to Tomcat 6.0. I waited until now for the plugins I use to be compatible. Now, all my plugins are compatible :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Motion Chart : An elegant chart demonstrating the evolutions of metrics build after build&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Quality Index : Compute a quality index for each project based on 4 axes : Coding, Complexity, Coverage and Style&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Radiator : Display a view like the main view of all projects (all the rectangles with a lot of colors) for all the components of a project&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rules Meter : Indicate for each project how many rules were activated during analysis&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;SCM Activity : Compute some metrics about the SCM Activity of the project&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;TagList : Analyze some tag (@TODO, @FIXME, ...) in your code and display them in the project&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Technical Debt : Compute a technical debt estimation for all the problems of your project&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Timeline : Display a chart of the evolution of the metrics build after build&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Build Stability : Display the stability of the builds on the continuous integration system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I made the first build of JTheque with Sonar 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first view, there is not a lot of changes with this new version, but the main view has been a little improved and the new analysis are good. Now you've metrics about your design and about the dependencies to cut to make your design better. They added a good dependency matrix to each project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version works well like the older. The only things to pay attention for the update is the long time the database upgrade takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also updated Hudson to the last version and also migrated it to my Tomcat 6.0.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>JTheque</category><category>Java</category><category>Sonar</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/05/first-build-jtheque-sonar-2-0.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2010 13:09:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The version 2.0 of Sonar has been released</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/03/sonar-2-0-released.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The developers of Sonar have just released the version 2.0 of Sonar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several major features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Architecture analysis : The architecture of the projects are now analyzed. We can see a matrix of project dependencies and a list of dependencies to delete to improve architecture quality.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Object oriented analysis : New metrics for the quality of the object oriented conception.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Improvements of the user interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only good stuff :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't test this new version, i will wait that my plugins be compatibles with the new version, but i will give informations of the new version once installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More informations on the &lt;a title="Sonar source" href="http://sonar.codehaus.org/sonar-2-0-in-screenshots/" target="_blank"&gt;Sonar website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Java</category><category>Releases</category><category>Sonar</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/03/sonar-2-0-released.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2010 14:27:25 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>