<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about thesis)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/thesis.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 05:49:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Publications: Deep Learning Features for Handwritten Keyword Spotting</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/04/publications-deep-learning-features-handwritten-keyword-spotting.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After my previous post about my publication on CPU performance optimization,
I wanted to talk a bit about two publications on Handwritten Keyword Spotting,
in which we extract features with Convolutional RBM RBM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We published two different papers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/306081095_Keyword_Spotting_with_Convolutional_Deep_Belief_Networks_and_Dynamic_Time_Warping"&gt;Keyword Spotting With Convolutional Deep Belief Networks and Dynamic Time Warping&lt;/a&gt;, in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Artificial Neural Networks (ICANN-2016), Barcelona, Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mixed Handwritten and printed digit recognition in Sudoku With Convolutional Deep Belief Network (Link will come), in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR-2016), Cancun, Mexico&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second paper is mostly a large extension of the first one, so I'll focus on
the complete version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side note, I also co-authored a third paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/312486359_Inkball_Models_as_Features_for_Handwriting_Recognition"&gt;Inkball Models as Features for Handwriting Recognition&lt;/a&gt;, in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Frontiers of Handwriting Recognition (ICFHR-2016), Shenzen, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mostly used our existing system to generate features for a comparison between
different set of features for handwritten keyword spotting. It was my first time
in China and I enjoyed the stay a lot. I also had the chance to meet my
girlfriend in Shenzen, all the more reason to mention this publication :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back on the main subject. The idea behind these publications is to
a Convolutional Deep Belief Network (CDBN) to extract features from the images
and then pass these features to either a Dynamic Time Warping (DTW) algorithm or
an Hidden Markov Model (HMM). The following image describe the overall system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Keyword Spotting System" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/kws_system.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The features are extracted from preprocessed normalized binary images. Using
a sliding window, moving from left to right, one pixel at a time, the features
are extracted on each window. The feature extractor is a Convolutional Deep
Belief Network, trained fully unsupervised. The features are then normalized so
that each feature group sum to one and then each has zero-mean and
unit-variance. The network used for feature extraction is depicted in the
following image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Convolutional Deep Belief Network features" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/kws_network.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two Convolutional Restricted Boltzmann Machines (CRBMs) are used, each followed
by a max pooling layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the features are extracted, they can be passed to the classifier for
keyword spotting scoring. We tested our features with two different approaches
for word scoring. The first one is a template matching strategy, Dynamic Time
Warping (DTW), is a very simple measure of distance between two sequences of
different length. The two sequences are warped non-linearly to minimize the
distance between each pair of features. A template from the training set is
compared to the word image being evaluated. This works pretty well for simple
data sets but fails when the writing styles of the test set are not known in the
training set. The second classifier is more powerful and trained, a Hidden
Markov Model (HMM). Character models are trained using the entire training set.
From these character models, a keyword model as well as an unconstrained model
(the filler model) are constructed. The probability of these two models is
computed using Viterbi and the final score is computed using log-odds scoring of
these two models using the filler model as a form of normalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique was evaluated on three datasets (George Washington (GW), Parzival
(PAR) and IAM offline database (IAM)). Our features were compared with three
reference feature sets, one heuristic and two local feature sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results for DTW:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Keyword Spotting Results with Dynamic Time Warping" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/kws_results_dtw.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, our features exhibit better performance than the other reference.
Except for the Mean Average Precision on the PAR data set. The very low
performance on PAR with DTW is explained by the fact mentioned earlier that it
has poor generalization to unknown writing styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results for HMM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Keyword Spotting Results with Hidden Markov Model" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/kws_results_hmm.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With HMM, our features are always better than the other feature sets. However,
the margin of improvement is smaller than when using DTW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the proposed system proved quite powerful and was able to outperform
the three tested feature sets on three datasets for keyword spotting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/word_spotting"&gt;C++ implementation on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for my thesis, I have finished the writings about a month ago and it is now
in the hands on my supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to have a look, the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/stories/publications.html"&gt;list of my publications&lt;/a&gt;
is available on this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more details on this project, don't hesitate to ask here or on
Github, or read the papers :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the next post about my publications will be about the finalization of my
thesis :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>deep learning</category><category>dll</category><category>publications</category><category>thesis</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/04/publications-deep-learning-features-handwritten-keyword-spotting.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 18:29:39 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>